<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo sermons, upon that great embassie of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ recorded by his Euangelist, Saint Matthew, Chap. 10.V.16. Preached by Iohn Scull, an humble professor and minister of the word.</title>
            <author>Scull, John, minister of the word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114766</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15170</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15170)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1584:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo sermons, upon that great embassie of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ recorded by his Euangelist, Saint Matthew, Chap. 10.V.16. Preached by Iohn Scull, an humble professor and minister of the word.</title>
                  <author>Scull, John, minister of the word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Snodham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15170:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS, VPON THAT GREAT EMBASSIE OF OVR LORD AND SAVIOVR IESVS CHRIST, Recorded by his Euangeliſt, Saint MATTHEW, Chap. 10. v. 16.</p>
            <p>Preached by IOHN SCVLL, an humble Profeſſor and Miniſter of the Word.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Snodham.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15170:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15170:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, THE RIGHT wel-deſeruing of Church, and Common-wealth, Sir HENRY WILLIAMS, Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Acile omnia tenenti, multa ſuperfluè</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. ep.</hi> 138. <hi>ad Hen. reg. Ang.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ingeruntur.</hi> Many words to a man of vnderſtanding, are more then enow. It was your deſire to haue ſome thing ſaid on this enſuing Text; your deſire to know, intimates your will to obſerue. <hi>Prius vtique eſt ſcire deum: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequens</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactant. de inſt: lib</hi> 6 <hi>cap</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>eſt colere.</hi> A man muſt know God, before he can ſerue him. It was your pleaſure to aſſigne me the Speaker; your choice argued your opinion: Oh that it were as eaſie for me to make good, as (for him that ſometimes ſaide) to ſay, <hi>Faciam vt iſta de me tua duplicetur opinio.</hi> It is now <note place="margin">Cic. Epiſt.</note> your propper goods; It is your goodneſſe to communicate it to the good of others. <hi>Bonum quo Communius, eo melius.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> The more common that a good thing is, the more good it will doe. <hi>Quibus parum, vel quibus nimium eſt, mihi ignoſcant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de Ciuit. Dei. li</hi> 22 <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>quibus autem ſatis eſt, non mihi, ſed domino mecum, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulantes, agant gratias.</hi> If ought be amiſſe, the fault is mine: If well, the praiſe is Gods.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15170:3"/>
And now, as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſpake to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dem.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: That as he reſpected them in all things, ſo they would him in this one: So alſo would I make bold, of you, to beg this fauour, that as I haue euer honoured your Vertues, and now ventured into the world to Obſerue you: ſo you would vouchſafe to Patronize my Obedience, a more acceptable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 22.</note> then the fat of Rammes, and to ſuffer it to paſſe vnder your name; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as an Argument of your <note place="margin">Iſocr. ad Dem.</note> Fauour, and my Reſpect. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Some body perhaps may be the better for it: you cannot be the worſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Though not <note place="margin">Iſocr. ſup.</note> the richer, yet the more renowned. Pleaſeth it you, that as you haue made your Houſe, as <hi>Obediahs</hi> Caues, to hide the Prophets of the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. 13.</note> Lord, and to feed them: ſo you would make your Name alſo, as the houſe of the Lord, to preſerue the Bookes of the Prophets, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect <note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22. 8.</note> them. And ſo I leaue this Suckling at the breaſts of your foſtering, and you and yours to the foſtering Father of the Church, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Totus in eo tuus cuius &amp; tu totus es. IOHN SCVLL.</signed>
               <note place="margin">
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Aug. ad Paulin. ep.</hi> 32.</bibl>
               </note>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15170:3"/>
            <head>The firſt SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MATH. 10. 16.</bibl>
               <q>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe in the midſt of Wolues: be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doues.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lus eſt in metuendo mali:</hi> (it was the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. Torq. ep. li.</hi> 6. <hi>ep.</hi> 82.</note> experience of a man many waies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned) <hi>quam in eo ipſo quod time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> the feare (commonly) is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the hurt, for we feare alwaies the worſt: and ſpeed better often times then we hoped. But <hi>Precogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum malum</hi> (as a great Philoſopher <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> obſerueth) <hi>minus offendit:</hi> that expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation <note place="margin">Superanda om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis fortuna fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo. Virg.</note> of ill, mitigates the extremity of the ill; for either we labour to preuent it, or reſolue to endure it.</p>
            <p>Chriſt Ieſus in this Text fore-warneth his Apoſtles of the hard meaſure that they ſhould meete with in the world, and becauſe they ſhould not thinke it vncouth when it came: hee thereupon warneth them, to be <hi>wiſe as Serpents,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Marl. in hunc locum.</note> and ſo to ſhunne it: to be <hi>innocent as Doues,</hi> and ſo to beare it.</p>
            <p>In the precedencie of this Chapter, Ieſus Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles with Commiſſion and Inſtruction: with Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Preach, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. for that is to doe the worke of an <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 5.</note> Euangeliſt: Secondly, to worke miracles, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix (as <hi>Beza</hi> ſpeakes) to the word: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignes and <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 12.</note> tokens (ſaith the Apoſtle) of an Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Hee ſent them with Commiſſion, their warrant for what they did: with Inſtruction: their Caution how to behaue themſelues, meekely or ſternely, as Heralds in Gods ſteed,
<pb facs="tcp:15170:4"/>
to denounce Peace or warre, according as they to whom they are ſent, are either worthy or vnworthy, <hi>verſe</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>But that iourney of theirs (like the Doues out of the Arke) <note place="margin">Gen. 8. 9.</note> was neither farre nor long: but, as was <hi>Dauids</hi> victorie ouer the Lyon and the beare; his encouragement to venture vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17. 34. <hi>Marl. ex Calu.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Goliah:</hi> ſo was that of theirs, <hi>Durioris militiae praeludia quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> their Preparatiue to this their ſecond, but longer, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and more dangerous Expedition.</p>
            <p>This Text then is but the Renewing of the former Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, with like Commiſſion and Inſtruction. <hi>Behold? ſend you, &amp;c.</hi> there is the Commiſſion: <hi>Be ye therefore, &amp;c.</hi> there is the Inſtruction. Theſe are the two eſſentiall parts of the body of this Text, either of which hath, (as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeakes of the <hi>Reuelation) tot Sacramenta quot verba,</hi> as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hier. ad Paulin. ep.</hi> 83.</note> myſteries as members. The firſt in the firſt is the Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to their Miſſion, in the firſt word, <hi>Behold:</hi> the ſecond is the power authorizing, in the ſecond word <hi>I: behold I:</hi> the third, the Miſſion, in the third word <hi>Send: Behold I ſend:</hi> the fourth, the Legates, in the fourth word <hi>You: Behold I ſend you:</hi> the fifth, the Oppoſition betweene them that are ſent, and them to whom they are ſent: the one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Sheepe: the other <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Wolues. The Inſtruction is an Imitation; firſt, of <hi>Serpents;</hi> ſecondly, of <hi>Doues:</hi> to learne Wiſedome of the one, and Innocencie of the other.</p>
            <p>Thus (as you ſee) haue I, like <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> croſt the next <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 23.</note> way; and brought you on the ſodaine (as was <hi>Habakkuk</hi> to <note place="margin">Dan. 14. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Babel)</hi> to the holy Citie; but you come not as <hi>Baladan</hi> to <note place="margin">Eſai. 39. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekias, to ſee:</hi> but as the Eunuch to <hi>Ieruſalem, to worſhip:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 8. 27.</note> and in the interim to ſpend ſome minutes in the Lords houſe, as the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> did moneths in <hi>Salomons,</hi> to <note place="margin">1 Reg. 10. 1.</note> learne the manner.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold, I ſend you</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Selah,</hi> in the old teſtament concludes ſome thing or <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hier. epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ep.</hi> 64.</note> other remarkeable, that went before: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Behold,</hi> in the new foreſhewes the like matter of note, in that that followes.</p>
               <p>To teach vs, that what manner of men God ſendeth into <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15170:4"/>
Church and common-wealth; to what conditioned men they be ſent, and how they conuerſe among vs, is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſpeciall note and conſequence. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Plato.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. As Gods hand of mercy or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is vpon Church or common-wealth; ſo accordingly doth he ſend good or euill Magiſtrates to gouerne them. He pittied the affliction of his people in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſent <note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> and he deliuered them vnder other perſecutors, as <hi>Chuſhan, Riſhathaim, Eglon, Iabin, Oreb, Zeb, Sihon, &amp;c,</hi> and ſent them <hi>Othniel, Ehud, Barak, Gideon, Iphtah, &amp;c.</hi> and they ſaued them. He ſaw their Shepheards turned Wolues: he ſent <hi>Dauid</hi> a good Shepheard, and he fed them. Againe, <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 23.</note> he would chaſtiſe their rebellion; Hee gaue them <hi>Ieroboam, Ahab, Zedekias, Reges in furore,</hi> Kings in his wrath, and they plagued them: he pittied his Church, and ſent <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Theodoſius, Helena, &amp;c.</hi> and they became Kings, her nurſing-fathers, and Queenes her nurſing-mothers: hee <note place="margin">Eſay 49. 23.</note> againe viſited her iniquitie, and gaue her <hi>Nero, Diocleſian, Iulian, &amp;c.</hi> and they perſecuted her; as a certaine religious man in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> wondred why it pleaſed God to make <hi>Phocas</hi> Emperour, an Angell (ſaith <hi>Anaſtatius)</hi> told him, <hi>Quia non inueni Peiorem:</hi> he was the worſt hee could <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anaſt. queſt. inſcript. q.</hi> 15.</note> meete with: and good enough was he (had he beene worſe) for that time and people. The ſame <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> tells vs like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of a certaine lewde vagabond, conſecrated (by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of an Angell) Biſhop of <hi>Thebaris,</hi> whom an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell alſo thus menaced: <hi>Cur ſuperbis et magnificè tibi places ò</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">An ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>infoelix? re vera non tanquam dignus ſacerdotio, factus es epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus: ſed quia haec ciuitas tali digna erat epiſcopo:</hi> What aileth thee thou wretch? and why magnifieſt thou thy ſelfe? it is not becauſe thou waſt worthy to be a Prieſt, that thou waſt made a Biſhop; but becauſe this Citie was worthy of no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Biſhop.</p>
               <p>Becauſe, an vnwiſe King deſtroyeth his people: (as <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> that ſinned, and made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne) but where they that be in authoritie, be men of vnderſtanding (as <hi>Salomon)</hi> there the citie flouriſheth, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 3. The good or ill
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15170:5"/>
Gouernor, is the bane or welfare of his charge.</p>
               <p>Becauſe, as the iudge of the people is himſelfe, ſo are his <note place="margin">2: Eccluſ. 10. 2.</note> officers: and what manner of man the Ruler of the Citie is, ſuch are all they that dwell therein: a wonder it was to ſee, how vnlike the <hi>Romans</hi> were to themſelues vnder <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> from what they were vnder <hi>Romulus,</hi> but that <hi>ipſi ſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liuius dec.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>in regis, velut vnici exempli mores formant.</hi> The greater will draw the leſſer: the ruler, the people. Like people, like <note place="margin">Eſai. 24. 2.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Cohen,</hi> Prince and Prieſt: it is the faſhion of the world to faſhion their betters. <hi>Regis ad exemplar totus componitur orbis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This might informe vs, how we ſtand to Godward, in <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> God his fauour or disfauour, in our Gouernours. Whether he hath ſent among vs ſheepe vnto ſheepe? as Chriſt the <note place="margin">Ioh. 1. 11.</note> lambe of God, to the faithfull, the flocke of Chriſt: or, Sheepe vnto Wolues? as the Prophets to the Iewes; or Wolues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Math. 23. 34.</note> Sheepe? as the Dragon after the woman; or finally <note place="margin">Apoc. 12. 13.</note> Wolues vnto Wolues? as <hi>Iehu</hi> to the houſe of <hi>Ahab.</hi> Hath <note place="margin">2 Reg. 10.</note> God ſent Sheepe vnto Sheepe? as when <hi>Iohn</hi> ſent to Chriſt, <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Ecce quàm bonum, Behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 133. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Brethren to dwell together in vnitie?</hi> or, hath hee ſent Sheepe vnto Wolues, as in my Text? the Inſtruction is the Vſe, <hi>be wiſe as Serpents, &amp;c.</hi> or hath he ſent Sheepe vnto Wolues, <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>that eate the fat, and cloath themſelues with the wooll: that kill them that are fed, but feede not the Sheepe: The harueſt indeed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 9. 37 38.</note> 
                  <hi>is great, but the labourers few: wherefore pray the Lord of the harueſt that he would ſend forth labourers into his harueſt:</hi> or, hath he ſent Wolues vnto Wolues, the Ichneumon to the Crocodile, that darts himſelfe into the belly of the Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile, and there eates what the other before had eaten: and when he hath liſt to come forth, hee makes his way by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a hole through the Crocodiles belly? <hi>They bite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure one another, take heed leſt yee be conſumed one of another.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 15.</note> When God ſends Sheepe vnto Sheepe, it is, <hi>that mercy and truth might meete together: that righteouſneſſe and peace might</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 85. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>kiſſe one another:</hi> when he ſends Sheepe vnto Wolues, it is, <hi>that vpon you might come all the righteous bloud that was ſhed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23. 35.</note>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15170:5"/>
                  <hi>vpon the earth:</hi> when he ſends Wolues vnto Sheepe, it is to prooue you, <hi>that the triall of your faith being much more preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>gold that periſheth (though it be tried with fire) might be found to your praiſe, and honour, and glory, at the appearing of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> When he ſends Wolues vnto Wolues, it is to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſinne with ſinne: when the young vipers eate their <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. hiſt. natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 62</note> way through their mothers belly when they were borne: to reuenge the death of their father, when they were begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Herein now appeareth the loue of God towards you, in ſending vnto you Sheepe, not Wolues. And here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine doe you turne mercy into iudgement, ſhould you to your ſhepheards proue Wolues, not Sheepe. Howſoeuer, God commands, and we muſt obey: Chriſt Ieſus ſends, and we muſt goe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold, I ſend.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>As the Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you;</hi> ſaid Ieſus to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: <note place="margin">Ioh. 20. 21.</note> The Father ſends, and the Sonne ſends: the Father ſends the Sonne, and the Sonne ſends the Apoſtles: the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſends the Sonne to reconcile the world to himſelfe. <hi>For it pleaſed the Father, that in him ſhould all fulneſſe dwell,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 1. 19. and 20.</note> 
                  <hi>and by him to reconcile all things vnto himſelfe: and to ſet at peace through the bloud of his Croſſe, both the things in earth, and the things in heauen:</hi> the Sonne ſends the Apoſtles to Preach this reconciliation by himſelfe: <hi>for God was in Chriſt, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>the world to himſelfe, not imputing their ſinnes vnto them: and hath committed to vs the word of Reconciliation:</hi> the Fathers Miſſion is the Sonnes Commiſſion: the Sonne ſends, and the Apoſtles Preach.</p>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus ſending is warrant for our Preaching: <hi>All</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>power is giuen to mee both in heauen and in earth: Goe therefore</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 18. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and teach all nations. I came downe from heauen, and haue done</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 6. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>my Fathers will on earth, and now all power is giuen to me in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and in earth. Ye haue beene witneſſes of my obedience: be ye</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 1. 8.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 5. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>alſo Heralds of my ſoueraigntie. Ye haue ſeene my ſufferings, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>glory. All power is giuen to mee in heauen and earth:</hi> The <note place="margin">Math. 17. 9.</note> moſt ioyfull tidings that euer came to heauen or earth. <note place="margin">Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15170:6"/>
                  <hi>Goe and teach all Nations: Preach the Goſpell to all creatures:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 16. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>the glad tidings of that New and better Couenant, that God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 7. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>and now by me contracteth with all Nations. In thy ſeed,</hi> (ſaid God vnto <hi>Abraham) ſhall all nations of the earth be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 22. 18.</note> there's the Promiſe. <hi>So God loued the world</hi> (ſaid the ſonne <note place="margin">Iohn. 3. 16.</note> of the ſame Father) <hi>that he hath giuen his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life:</hi> there's the Performance. <hi>This is my beloued Sonne</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (ſaid the Father of the Sonne) <hi>in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>heare him:</hi> there's obedience enioyned vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But how ſhall they heare without a Preacher? and how ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 14. 15. <hi>Petr. Longab. in cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ad Rom.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>they Preach except they be ſent? Credere ex auditu eſt: audire ex Praedicatione: Praedicare ex Miſſione:</hi> Faith comes by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, hearing comes by Preaching; and Preaching comes by the authoritie of Ieſus Chriſts ſending.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold, I ſend.</head>
               <p>No man may take vpon him any Authoritie, vnleſſe he <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> be lawfully called. <hi>No man taketh this honour vnto himſelfe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 5. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron. When <hi>Brennus</hi> had taken <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> that eſcaped to <hi>Veies,</hi> inſtantly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned <note place="margin">Plut. Camil.</note> 
                  <hi>Camillus</hi> (then a baniſhed man in <hi>Ardea)</hi> in that common calamity, to become their Dictator; but he by no meanes would accept of that tranſcendent honour, till ſuch time as they that were beſieged within the Capitole, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy preſentatiue of the State, confirmed his election by their Suffrages: Thus <hi>Numa</hi> contented not himſelfe with electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Plut. Numa.</note> of <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Sabines,</hi> till inauguration from heauen confirmed him King of <hi>Rome.</hi> For when <hi>Tatius</hi> his ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne with <hi>Romulus,</hi> had made of both Nations one peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: it was in the firſt <hi>Interregnum</hi> concluded, that the one ſhould chooſe the King, but out of the body of the other: ſo to engage him to either ſide: to the one, for that they choſe him; to the other, for that he was of their Nation. Now though <hi>Numa</hi> were thus choſen by a wonderfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of both Nations, yet put he not on the imperiall Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme, till he conſulted with heauen, to confirme his calling
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15170:6"/>
on earth. It is a Praeminire by the lawes of <hi>England</hi> to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpe authoritie without authoritie, but as all men agree of the name of Happineſſe, to call it (as the Philoſoper obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet are there (if <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arro</hi> in <hi>Auguſtine</hi> recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arles. ethic.</hi> 1.</note> right) 288. differing opinions, what it ſhould be: ſo <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 19.</note> all acknowledge a power authorizing, but differ about the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ciuit. dei. cap.</hi> 1.</note> perſons authorized, who they ſhould be.</p>
               <p>The pronouncing of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> ſhewed <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> who was an <hi>Ephramite,</hi> and who a <hi>Gileadite.</hi> The <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iudic. 12. 6.</note> in ſtead of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> pronounced <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth:</hi> Like our <hi>Iriſh</hi> that cannot ſound the letter <hi>H.</hi> So <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 18. 30.</note> by the <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> points out the able Miniſter: and <hi>Iethro</hi> by the foure Cardinall Vertues, the compleate <note place="margin">Exod. 18. 21.</note> Magiſtrate: the <hi>Vrim</hi> in the Miniſter is the puritie of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the <hi>Thummim,</hi> the ſinceritie of his life. In the firſt, we are <hi>light, to illuminate;</hi> in the ſecond, <hi>ſalt, to ſeaſon others:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>but if the light that be in thee bee darkeneſſe, how great is that</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>13</label> 
                  <hi>darkeneſſe? If the ſalt hath loſt its ſauour, wherewith ſhall it bee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 6 23.</note> 
                  <hi>ſalted? it is thenceforth good for nothing but to be caſt out,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>and to bee troden vnder foot of men. Let your light ſo</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>16</label> 
                  <hi>ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi> Preaching is as the body of <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> good life: good life as the ſoule of Preaching. Now as the body without the ſoule is dead, ſo is Preaching without good life; and this is the Miniſters <hi>Shibboleth.</hi> Now whether it be they that haue the <hi>Vrim</hi> and want the <hi>Thummim,</hi> or haue the <hi>Thummim</hi> and want the <hi>Vrim:</hi> eyther vncapable, as <hi>Vzziah</hi> to meddle with the Arke: or vnworthie, as <hi>Simon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Magus</hi> to diſpoſe of the holy Ghoſt: theſe may be of <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8. 18.</note> but not of God his making, Prieſts: intruders, not Apoſtles. <hi>I haue not ſent theſe Prophets</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 23. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>yet they ran: I haue not ſpoken vnto them, and yet they Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, when they that ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> chayre, as the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Scribes and Phariſes, but participate not of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpirit, as thoſe <hi>ſeauentie: that reſpect perſons, and iudge for reward: that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Num. 11. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>with the current of the world, ſeeke their owne, and nor that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Micah 3. 11.</note>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15170:7"/>
                  <hi>which is Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> They happily be ſent: but as <hi>Antiochus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to Ieruſalem to vndoe vs. But as the faithfull Miniſter is <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the diſpoſer of the myſteries of God: <hi>As</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>if God by him beſought you;</hi> So is the ſincerely dealing Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> gods miniſter, if thou doeſt well <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for thy good: if thou doeſt euill, then is he <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> a reuenger of gods wrath for thy naughtineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold I ſend you.</head>
               <p>Fiſher-men (for the moſt part) ſimple and vnlearned ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, Non de foro Iuſtiniano, ſed de ſimplicitate</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Serme de Apoſt.</note> 
                  <hi>piſcatoria,</hi> not out of the Doctors Commons great Clarkes and learned in the Law; but out of the company of fiſher-men, ſimple and illiterate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brethren, you ſee your calling: how that not many wiſe men</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called. But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>wiſe, and God hath choſen the weake things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>27</label> 
                  <hi>the mighty things, the vile things of the world, and things</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>28</label> 
                  <hi>which are deſpiſed hath God choſen, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are. That no fleſh ſhould reioyce in his</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>29</label> 
                  <hi>preſence. In homine triaſunt ex quibus oritur omnis humana glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatio.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hugo Card in</hi> 1 Cor. 1.</note> Man takes occaſion; either in his ſoule, becauſe of his wiſedome, or in his fleſh, becauſe of his nobility, or laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in outward things, becauſe of his might and riches, but God ſaith the Apoſtle, hath choſen <hi>Non multos ſapientes,</hi> not <hi>many wiſe men,</hi> and that (ſaith the Cardinall) confounds the <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> firſt, vaine boaſting. <hi>Non multos nobiles;</hi> not many noble men, and that confounds the ſecond. <hi>Non multos po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes,</hi> not many mighty men, and that confounds the third, <hi>That no fleſh might glory in his preſence. That the wiſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 9. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>man glory not in his wiſedome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength, nor the rich man in his riches.</hi> But as it is written, <hi>He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>let him reioyce in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God bringeth to paſſe the purpoſe of his owne good pleaſure either; with meanes, as when hee ſaued <hi>Noah</hi> by <note place="margin">Gen. 7. 1.</note> meanes of an arke: or with ſmall meanes; <hi>as when he ſed</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15170:7"/>
                  <hi>fiue thouſand men, beſide women and children, with fiue loaues</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> 
                  <hi>and two fiſhes;</hi> Or without meanes: <hi>as when he made all things</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>of nothing, onely he ſpake and it was done, he commanded and it</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 33 9. 2 Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtood faſt:</hi> Or againſt meanes: <hi>as when he ſweetned ſalt water with ſalt.</hi> The Remora or Echeneis is a little fiſh, of but halfe a foot long, and yet ſtates a ſhip though vnder ſaile with neuer ſo good a forewind. Blow the wind (ſaith <hi>Pliny)</hi> how <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. hiſt. nat. l.</hi> 32 <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> it will, rage, ſtorme and tempeſt, what they can, labour hundreds at the oare with might and maine, as ſometimes at <hi>Anthonies</hi> admirall, and <hi>Caligulaes</hi> galliace; if ſhe arreſt, no violence is able to reſcue. The Miniſter is the leaſt of the fingers of God; and yet is he powerfull ouer the creatures of God. <hi>Dedit Dominus poteſtatem Apoſtolis, ſuper Naturam,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. ſerm. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt.</note> 
                  <hi>vt eam curarent: ſuper Daemones, vt eos euerterent: ſuper Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, vt ipſa immutarent: ſuper Mortem, vt eam contemnerent: ſuper Angelos, vt corpus domini conſecrarent.</hi> God hath giuen <note place="margin">Apoſtolicall power.</note> to his Apoſtles (and their ſucceſſours) power ouer nature, diuels, elements, death, Angels: Ouer nature to heale her, Heale the ſick, cleanſe the leapers: Ouer diuels, to caſt them <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 8.</note> out; <hi>Lord euen the diuels are ſubdued to vs through thy name:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 10. 17.</note> Ouer elements to change them, Elements into Sacraments: <hi>Detrahe verbum ab aqua, &amp; quid erit niſi aqua? accedat ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. hom.</hi> 80.</note> 
                  <hi>ad elementum, &amp; fit ſacramentum:</hi> Take the word from the water (in Baptiſme) and what will it be but water? adde the word vnto the element, and it becomes a Sacrament: Ouer death to contemn it, by dying to triumph ouer death, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 54.</note> for to ſwallow vp death in victory: Ouer Angells to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate bread and wine, the bleſſed Sacrament, of the body and bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, a grace denyed to Angells and Archangels, to Principalities and Powers, to Vertues, Throanes, and Dominions, to Cherubins and Seraphins: They onely that are ſent to preach, haue power to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate. Power as the Miniſter of God, ouer the creatures of God: <hi>Elias</hi> ouer the fire, to purſue the water, like the raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe, <note place="margin">1 Reg. 18. 38.</note> the cloudes, and to licke it vp like oyle: as alſo ouer the aire to be cleere or cloudy, ſunne-ſhine, or raine. <hi>Moſes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 5. 17.</note> ouer the ſea, to turne it to dry land: ouer the land, to turne <note place="margin">Ex. 14. 21.</note>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15170:8"/>
the duſt thereof into lyce. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ouer the ſunne and moone, <note place="margin">Ex 8. 16.</note> to ſtand-ſtill, the one in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> the other in the valley of <hi>Aeialon,</hi> till the Lords people auenged themſelues on their <note place="margin">Ioſh. 10. 12.</note> enemies. Thus we ſee the miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt, powerfull <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>13</label> ouer the creatures of God: <hi>that at the name of Ieſus euery knee ſhould bow: both of things in heauen, and things in earth,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 10. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and things vnder the earth, and that euery tongue ſhould confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt is the Lord, vnto the glory of God the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Would ye be without feare of the Magiſtrate? doe well <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> then, <hi>for Rulers are not to be feared for good workes, but for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Would ye haue comfort of the Miniſter? receiue him <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> as the <hi>Galathians</hi> receiued the Apoſtle, as an angell of God, <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 14.</note> yea, as Chriſt Ieſus: as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did Chriſt, ioyfully, they come to you as Chriſt to Ieruſalem, Meekely: meekely and <note place="margin">Mat. 21. 5.</note> ſimply like ſheepe: meekely without pride: ſimply with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraud.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nihilo robuſtieres, vel magis pares, ad vim hoſtium repellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Marlor. in hunc locum.</note> 
                  <hi>quàm ſint oues contra luporum rabiem.</hi> No more able to conteſt with the malice of the wicked, then the filly ſheepe to daunt the fury of wolues: tyed notwithſtanding to preach the word, and that with all boldneſſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 4. 29.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> 6. 10 <hi>ethie.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Boldly and confidently ſtand in the profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt and his word, conſidering, not their owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilities to reſiſt, but Chriſts deſignement, that ſet them on worke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15170:8"/>
               <head>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell rows="2">1. In diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature.</cell>
                        <cell>Meeke: <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, not dominee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 3.</note>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="5">Sheepe</cell>
                        <cell>Simple: <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, not hypocritizing. <note place="margin">Math. 7. 15.</note> 
                           <hi>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe in the middeſt of Wolues:</hi> not that others crueity ſhould turne you into Wolues; but that wolues aſſwaged by your gentlenes might be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Sheepe. You muſt be in diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature, meeke and ſimple as Sheep. <note place="margin">Marlor. in hunc locum.</note> 
                           <hi>Ouibus nihil eſt ſimplicius,</hi> nothing more ſimple, and without guile: <hi>nihil innocenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> nothing more innocent, and without offering wrong: <hi>nihilmagis imbelle,</hi> more weake, and leſſe reſiſting wrong.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell rows="4">to feed</cell>
                        <cell>1. The body with bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. 13.</note> as <hi>Obediah</hi> fed the Prophets.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell rows="3">2. the ſoule with</cell>
                        <cell>1. The word, to win them to Chriſt, the power of <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> God vnto ſaluation.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="4">2 vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</cell>
                        <cell>2. The Sacraments; to incorporate them into Chriſt, as the branches <note place="margin">Iohn 15. 5.</note> in the vine.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. Their owne liues <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 17.</note> (ſhould there becauſe) to be offered vp vpon the ſacrifice and ſeruice of their faith.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell rows="2">to clothe</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1. The body with ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Iob 31. 20.</note> as <hi>Iob</hi> with his fleece.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2. The ſoule with truth, <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 14.</note> righteouſnes, peace, faith, &amp;c.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15170:9"/>
                  <hi>Meminiſſe debemus quo vocabulo Chriſtus gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gem ſuum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellat,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr. Serm.</hi> 2 <hi>de zelo &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quo nomine nuncupat: Oues vocat, vt innocentia Chriſtiana ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s aequet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Agnos vocat, vt agnorum naturam ſimplicem, ſimplicitas mentis inn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>etur:</hi> We muſt remember how Chriſt called his flocke; what title he attributed vnto them. Hee called them Sheepe, he called them Lambes; Sheepe for their innocency, Lambes for their ſimplicitie: To teach vs that men of eminent place, in Church and Common-wealth, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> muſt not be imperious, but meeke. <hi>If a man be fallen, by occaſion, into any fault, ye which are ſpirituall reſtore ſuch a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with the ſpirit of meeknes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ea eſt animantium omnium natura, vt manſuetudine potius quam violentia reguntur:</hi> Such is the nature of all creatures, that it is wonne, rather by gentleneſſe then auſterity, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Man, <hi>animal ſui iuris,</hi> a creature, ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> at his owne <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> diſpoſe, and not ſo eaſily awed as wooed. <hi>Blandienti poſſum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. epiſt.</hi> 40. <hi>ad Ruffinam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ac quieſcere, non timeo comminantem:</hi> I can (ſaith <hi>Hierome)</hi> be contented to be intreated, but menacing cannot diſaſter me.</p>
               <p>Hence it was that <hi>Alphonſus</hi> often walked without his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Panormit. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de reb. g. Alphon. Plut. Num.</hi>
                  </note> gard, but <hi>Numa</hi> vtterly diſcharged them: in token that they were Sheepe, not Wolues: meeke, not imperious: inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, not iniurious; and loued rather to be loued then fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>There is no ſurer guard to a Prince, then the perfect loue and good will of his Subiects. There is no ſuch way to <note place="margin">Plut. Arat.</note> winne their loue as gentleneſſe. There is no ſuch way, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Magiſtrate to inſinuate himſelfe into the heart of the people; or for the Miniſter to worke vpon the heart, as for the one and the other to be calme, where they might be rough: to be Sheepe where they might be Wolues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</head>
               <p>Sheepe (ſaith <hi>Pliny)</hi> are in great requeſt, both in regard <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. natur. l.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>cap.</hi> 67.</note> that they ſerue for ſacrifices: as alſo by reaſon that their fleece yeelds ſo profitable an vſe. Not onely the heathen ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed Sheepe to pacifie their falſe gods (deuills, whom <note place="margin">Pſal. 96. 5.</note> they worſhipped in ſtead of God) but the true worſhippers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15170:9"/>
of the One and true God, celebrated yeerely their Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">Exod. 12. 24.</note> with this ſacrifice: and was beſides a perpetuall peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offering <note place="margin">Leuit. 3. 7.</note> for ſinne.</p>
               <p>Good gouernours, in Church and Common-wealth, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> ſpend euen their liues, for the good of Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: <hi>A good Shepheard giueth his life for his Sheepe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 10. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Baiazetts</hi> praier for his army, was much like <hi>Dauid</hi> his prayer for the people: To dye himſelfe deſeruedly for his credulity; rather then ſo many Innocents ſhould be ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as Sheepe, vndeſeruedly, for him. <hi>I haue ſinned</hi> (ſaid <hi>Dauid) yea, I haue done wickedly: but theſe Sheepe, what haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam 24. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>they done? Let thy hand, I pray thee, be againſt me, and againſt my fathers houſe.</hi> The two <hi>Decij,</hi> the Father and the Sonne, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liu. decad.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Luendis periculis publicis piacula,</hi> as ſacrifices, to free the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth from danger, deuoted themſelues for their armies: So did <hi>Codrus</hi> for the Athenians; for when in the warre of <hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> he vnderſtood by Oracle that that ſide <note place="margin">Herodot.</note> ſhould haue the victory, whoſe captaine ſhould be ſlaine: he tooke vpon him the habit of a poore common ſouldier, and ſo became a ſacrifice for his countrey. When <hi>Pompey</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plut. Pomp.</note> (on <hi>Syllas</hi> behalfe) would haue put all the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mertines</hi> to the ſword, <hi>Sthenius,</hi> a gouernour among the <hi>Hymerians,</hi> tooke all the fault vpon himſelfe, telling <hi>Pompey,</hi> that it was hee that had perſwaded his friends, and compelled his enemies to doe as they did. <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> a law-giuer among the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plut. Lycurg.</note> after that he had ſworne them to the vnuiolable keeping of his lawes till his returne, thruſt himſelfe into perpetuall exile; becauſe that hee would haue the lawes that he had made for their good perpetually kept. Theſe were good Platoniſts, borne not for themſelues, but for their countrey.</p>
               <p>Your Skarlet then is not this peoples, but your owne <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> blood, that you (ye Iudges) muſt be euer ready to ſpend for them. <hi>Our Lawne, the robe of purity, whitned in the bloud</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 7. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lambe. We muſt not be found to ſeeke,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>but</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>not yours, but you;</hi> nor you ſeeke to be found, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, neuer a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the richer, but a great deale the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15170:10"/>
more honourabler, by your places. When you reckon your liuing, you may value your reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ues, but not your office. <hi>Habere enim queſtui rempub: non modo turpe eſt: ſed &amp; ſceleſtum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cic. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>offic.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; nefarium.</hi> To riſe by the ruine of the Common-wealth, is abhomination: to vndoe many to make One, is both ſin and ſhame; it is to be a wolfe, and not a Sheepe. Whereas thoſe that Chriſt in my text ſends, muſt bee Sheepe, not Wolues, in diſpoſition of nature, meeke and ſimple: vſefull towards others to feede and clothe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</head>
               <p>Simon <hi>thou ſonne of</hi> Iona, loueſt thou mee more then <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 15.</note> theſe? <hi>He ſaid vnto him,</hi> yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I loue thee. He ſaid vnto him, feede my Lambes. He ſaid to him againe the ſecond time. <hi>Simon,</hi> thou ſonne of <hi>Iona,</hi> loueſt thou me? he <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>16</label> ſaid vnto him, yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I loue thee. Hee ſaid vnto him, Feede my Sheepe. He ſaid vnto him the third time, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> thou ſonne of <hi>Iona,</hi> louest thou me! <hi>Peter</hi> was ſorry be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaid vnto him the third time, loueſt thou me? and ſaid vnto him, Lord thou knoweſt all things: thou knoweſt that I loue thee. Ieſus ſaid vnto him, Feed my Sheepe. <hi>He asked him thrice, that a threefold confeſſion might make amends for a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold deniall: but all the matter in charge was of feeding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Gouernours muſt be Feeders.</hi> Dauid <hi>fed</hi> Iſrael: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> Barzillai, Dauid. <hi>The widdow fed the Prophet, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 72.</note> 
                  <hi>the Children of the Prophets.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 32.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Take heede therefore vnto your ſelues, and to all the flocke <note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 17. 15.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. 38.</note> whereof the Holy Ghoſt hath made you ouer-ſeers, to feede the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his owne bloud. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Take heede to your ſelues, for he that hath no care of his owne ſaluation, will haue none alſo of others. Take heede</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mar. ex Cal.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto your ſelues, and all the flocke: for a man ſhall anſwer, not onely for himſelfe, but for all alſo vnder his charge.</hi> I come againſt the ſhepheards (ſaith the Lord) and will require <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 10.</note> my Sheepe at their hands. <hi>Take heede vnto your ſelues, and to the flocke, to feede the Church of God. Firſt,</hi> exemple <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> Conuerſationis, <hi>by example of good life: becauſe</hi> plus mouent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15170:10"/>
exempla quam verba, <hi>example is more powerfull with the multitude then precept. Secondly,</hi> verbo Praedicationis, <hi>by preaching of tho Word: becauſe</hi> the Prieſts lippes ſhould <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 7.</note> preſerue knowledge, and the people ſhould ſeeke the Law at his mouth. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Fructis Orationis, <hi>by his continuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for them.</hi> God forbid that I ſhould ſinne againſt the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 23.</note> Lord, and ceaſe praying for you.</p>
               <p>Woe vnto the Shepheards of Iſraell that feede themſelues: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Should not the ſhepheards feede the flocke? Woe to the ignorant <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 2.</note> and couetous ſhepheards, for they are dogges, not ſhepheards. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa</hi> 56. 10.</note> The ignorant dumbe dogges. The couetous greedy dogges. Woe to the mercileſſe and cruell Shepheard, that ſtrengtheneth <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>11</label> not the weake, that healeth not the ſicke, that bindeth not vp the broken, nor brought againe that which was driuen away, nor ſought that which was loſt, that with cruelty and with ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 4.</note> ruleth them. <hi>Theſe, whether they be Miniſters or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, are butchers, not Shepheards: Wolues not Sheepe. Whereas good gouernours muſt bee Sheepe not Wolues. Sheepe in nature; Sheepe in vſe, not onely to feede, but to clothe alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</head>
               <p>The Oxe is of principall vſe for the belly, the Sheepe for the backe: the Oxe for our dayly foode, the Sheepe for our apparrell: for euen as men bee beholding to the Oxe for their principall foode which they labour for: ſo muſt they acknowledge, that they haue their cloathing and couerture from the ſilly Sheepe.</p>
               <p>Chriſtian prelacy doth not onely feede, but clothe alſo. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>I put on iuſtice and it couered me: my iudgement was as aroabe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iob 29. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and a crowne. In</hi> Aarons <hi>Miter was engrauen</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Ex. 39. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>holineſſe vnto the Lord.</hi> His roabes were of foure ſeuerall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours: the embrodering a bell and a Pomegranate, and all to ſhew how Gods Miniſters muſt bee cloathed. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription <note place="margin">Hieron. deritu &amp; veſte ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dot.</note> in his crowne, is the deſcription of his life: The foure ſeuerall colours, the foure diſtinct elements of the world: the embroydering of the bell, the ſound of his preaching: the many kernells in the Pomegranate, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vertues of his life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15170:11"/>
                  <hi>The Kings daughter is all glorious within: her cloathing is of</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>wrought gold.</hi> Glorious ſhe is within: rich without: with <note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 14.</note> inward holineſſe; with outward righteouſneſſe: her cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is of wrought gold. Of all mettals; Firſt, <hi>Puriſsimum, ſine ſulphuritate comburente,</hi> moſt pure, without ſoyling. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Molliſſimum,</hi> tender and of large extent, as one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neere into an hundred and twenty leaues. Thirdly, <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſsimum,</hi> exceeding ponderous, <hi>ob diuturnam conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctionem, firmiſsimam compoſitionem,</hi> by reaſon of long concoction, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin hiſt. natur. l.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> firme compoſition. Fourthly, <hi>Suauiſsimum,</hi> very ſweet, by reaſon of the excellency of the temperature comforting the heart, and ſtrengthening the ſpirits. The Church of God is a Virgin, pure as the Sonne: meeke and mild as the lambe: chaſte as the Doue: ſweet as the Roſe: The Virgins <note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 15.</note> her fellowes, the Angells of light, like vnto her, ſhall beare her company: In ſtead of fathers ſhee ſhall haue children <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> borne; vnto her, <hi>non modo ſermonis &amp; vocis incitamento, ſed fidei, &amp; virtutis exemplo:</hi> By her ſoule-ſauing words, loyall <note place="margin">Cyprian ad Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium Papam.</note> loue, and workes of grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>She is the woman cloathed with the Sun, &amp; the moone is vnder</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 12. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>her feete. O let her Prieſts be cloathed with righteouſneſſe: let</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 132. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>her Saints reioyce and ſing. Her eyes are like the doues: Ob let</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 4. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>their voyces be like the Angells, the Lambes euerlaſting Goſpell.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Shee is the Lillie among the thornes.</hi> Make them good God, <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 2.</note> oh make them Sheepe amidſt the Wolues. <hi>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the midſt of Wolues.</head>
               <p>Diuers countryes are ſubiect to diuers annoyances. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke</hi> to Locuſts. <hi>Italy</hi> to Scorpions. <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to Crocodiles. <hi>France</hi> to Wolues: but the common plague that infecteth the whole world, is the Wolfe <hi>feritas,</hi> (to diſtinguiſh with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cic offic. l.</hi> 3.</note> the Orator) <hi>in figura hominis,</hi> the Man-wolfe, and his cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Depoſite homine in ſylueſtre animal tranſiens,</hi> when a man <note place="margin">Seneca de Clem. ad Neronem.</note> leaues to be a man, and degenerates into a Wolfe.</p>
               <p>Cruelty is a Wolfe, tyrannizing ouer all parts of the world. It began in <hi>Caine,</hi> ſince is ſpred ouer all nations, <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 8.</note>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15170:11"/>
times and places. It was the entertainment that <hi>Lot</hi> found <note place="margin">Gen. 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> among the Sodomites, <hi>Sampſon</hi> among the Philiſtims, <note place="margin">Iudg. 16. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieremy</hi> in Aegypt, <hi>Ezechiel</hi> at Babel, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> at Rome, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Bartholmew</hi> in India, <hi>Iames</hi> at Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>Philip</hi> at Hierapolis, <hi>Andrew</hi> at Ideſſa: in a word whereſoeuer the Apoſtles be in expediting their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there are they as <hi>Dauid</hi> betweene <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Achiſh.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17. <hi>Calu. in Pſal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vnica onis inter duas Luporum turmas.</hi> Inuironed (as the center with the circumference) round about with Wolues.</p>
               <p>This ſhould teach vs to walke warily, blameleſſe and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> pure as the ſonnes of God without rebuke, in the midſt <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> of a naughty and crooked nation. Becauſe <hi>ad innumeros telorum iactus, expoſita eſt hominum vita.</hi> Cruelty hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cal. in Pſal.</hi> 34.</note> inſtruments of death thirſting after blood, the blood of the faithfull ſpecially, <hi>Qui velut oues ſunt in medio lupo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Who are as Sheepe in the midſt of Wolues. Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the midſt of Wolues.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The naturall man perceiueth not the things of the Spirit of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>God, for they are fooliſhneſſe vnto him: neither can hee know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned. Non tantum non</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mar. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>intelligit, ſed ne aſſentitur quidem ijs rebus quas docet ſpiritus dei.</hi> As he knowes them not, ſo neither doth he approoue of them.</p>
               <p>To teach vs, that men before they be regenerate, be no <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> better then bruite beaſts, Lyons, Leopards, Beares, and Wolues. Chriſt called <hi>Herod</hi> a Foxe. <hi>Ieremy</hi> called <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 3. 32. Ier. 31. 18.</note> a Calfe. <hi>Daniel</hi> calls the Aſſyrians a Lyon: the Perſians a Beare: the Graecians, a Leopard: <hi>Darius,</hi> a <note place="margin">Dan. 7. 4. 5. &amp; 6.</note> Ramme, and <hi>Alexander,</hi> a Goate. <hi>Amos</hi> calles the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">Dan. 8. 3. &amp; 5.</note> of Samaria, Cowes, <hi>Iohn</hi> calls the Iewes, Vipers. Chriſt <note place="margin">Amos 4. 1.</note> Ieſus in the text calls the bloody &amp; vnregenerate, Wolues. <note place="margin">Math. 3. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Herod</hi> was a foxe for his ſubtlety, <hi>Ephraim,</hi> a calfe for his wantonneſſe: the Aſſyrians, a Lyon for their haughtines: the Perſeans a Beare for their boyſterouſneſſe: the Greeks,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15170:12"/>
a Leopard for their Polyarchies: <hi>Darius,</hi> a Ramme for his forces: <hi>Alexander,</hi> a Goat or Roe-bucke for his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: the Samaritanes, Cowes for their baſeneſſe: the Iewes, Vipers for their Parricids, and Wolues for their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty. <hi>Ouid</hi> moralatizeth <hi>Lycaont</hi> cruelty when hee meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorphizeth <note place="margin">Metamorph.</note> him into a Wolfe; and ſo wee likewiſe ſee what manner of man <hi>Demenetus Parrhaeſius</hi> was, who in a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. hiſt. natur. l.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 22.</note> ſolemne ſacrifice that the Arcadians wickedly celebrated vnto <hi>Iupiter Lyceus,</hi> taſted of the intralls of a child, and ſo was turned into a wolfe. Such were the family of the <hi>Antai,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> of which one euery yeare, was transformed into a Wolfe. Little and better were <hi>Veſpatian</hi> and <hi>Nero.</hi> The one of which made his officers to ſerue his turne as ſpunges, firſt <note place="margin">Sueton.</note> to ſoake them in the fatte of other men, and then to ſqueeze them, as goods confiſcate to himſelfe. The others care was, <hi>Ne quis quid habeat;</hi> that no man but himſelfe if it were poſſible ſhould be worth a groat.</p>
               <p>Such a one (ſaid <hi>Socrates</hi> to <hi>Zopyrus)</hi> had I beene, had <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> not the inſtruction of Philoſophy amended the ill diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my nature. Oh did the light of nature then through the glymbring of grace change Wolues into Sheepe, and ſhall not now the light of grace, through the preaching of Gods word, keepe Sheepe from degenerating into wolues! Did the words of men, through a little illumination, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with a Heathen to liue as a Chriſtian? and ſhall not the word of God, through the Sunne-ſhine of grace, keepe Chriſtians from liuing like Heathen? <hi>Is not my word euen</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 23. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>like a fire, ſaith the Lord? and like a hammer that breaketh the ſtone.</hi> Mans heart is as yron, the word of God as fire to ſoften it, and as a hammer to worke it to his owne good will and pleaſure. It is as a ſtone, but the hammer of Gods word worketh it into a well pleaſing ſacrifice of a broken <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 17.</note> and contrite heart: It is liuely and mighty in operation. <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> Then let vs flye vnto it for reformation; ſo ſhall the Wolfe dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lye with the <note place="margin">Eſa. 11. 6.</note> Kid, and the Calfe with the Lyon, and the fat beaſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and a little child ſhall leade them. The Cow and the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15170:12"/>
Beare ſhall feede; their young ones ſhall lye together: and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> the Lyon ſhall eate ſtraw like the Bullocke: and the ſucking Childe ſhall play vpon the hole of the Aſpe: and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Childe ſhall put his hand vpon the Cockatrice hole. <hi>Eſa</hi> 11. 6.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sibylla apud lac. inſt. di. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Word for word in a manner, as if <hi>Sybil</hi> had beene to tranſlate the Prophet into Greeke meeter. <hi>Then ſhall none hurt nor deſtroy in all the mountaine of mine holineſſe.</hi> Eſa. 11. 9.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nec lupus inſide as pecori: nec retia ceruis <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Virg. eglog.</hi> 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vlla dolum meditantur.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But the Apoſtles in the meane time are ſent as ſheepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the middeſt of Wolues.</head>
               <p>Had he ſent them among Lyons, there might bee hope that ſubmiſſion might purchaſe pacification: but to crouch to the Wolfe, is to deſpaire, and dye. The Lyon is a chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, though bloudy, yet generous: but the Wolfe is a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and inſulteth ouer miſery.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Corpora magnanimo ſatis eſt proſtraſſe Leoni. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ouid. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de Triſt. elog.</hi> 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pugna ſuum finem cum iacet hoſtis, habet.</l>
                  <l>At lupus, &amp; turpes inſtant morientibus vrſi:</l>
                  <l>Et quacun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> minor nobilitate fera eſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The Iſraelites, as ſilly ſheepe, were grieuouſly oppreſſed vnder the Wolues their Taske-maſters; and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 5. 7.</note> the Maſter-wolfe commanded to lay more vpon them. The poore Countrey-man is grieuouſly taxed with a long rent, byting brokage, deepe gratification; and the tyrannizing Land-lord, griping Vſurer, and extorting Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, cry ſtill with the Leech, <hi>Giue, Giue.</hi> Prou. 30. 15. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> lay at the rich mans gate a Lazer indeed, full of ſores,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15170:13"/>
and affamiſhed. The dogges lent him their tongues, <note place="margin">Luc. 16. 21.</note> to licke his ſoares, but no man vouchſafed him a crumme from the dogges to ſtay his ſtomacke.</p>
               <p>The greedy guts of this World are without all feeling of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> others miſery. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> beſought his brethren in the anguiſh of his ſoule: they ſaw it, but would not heare him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cum penes crudelitatem ſit timeri, penes nos ſit odiſſe:</hi> Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> ſcarres other men with feare, it ſelfe with hatred; and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al. max. l.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Suet.</hi>
                  </note> comes at laſt to be as fearefull of others as hated. <hi>Nero</hi> kept poyſon in a boxe; <hi>Cleopatra</hi> Vipers, to preuent their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties deſerued hatred. <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> truſted neither friend nor <note place="margin">Plut. Arat.</note> ſeruant to lodge within his Court gates. <hi>Herod</hi> was afraid <note place="margin">Math. 2. 3.</note> of his owne ſon, as well as the Infants, leaſt he as wel as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might proue to be Chriſt, and ſo ſent him packing as <note place="margin">Joſeph. antiq.</note> well as them. Cruelty is euer fearefull in it ſelfe, and hated of others; and God one time or other payes it home in its owne kinde. Therefore were <hi>Iacobs</hi> ten brethren impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 17. <hi>We</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>as they communed together, haue verily ſinned againſt our brother, in that we ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoule, when he beſought vs, and wee would not heare him:</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>21</label> 
                  <hi>Therefore is this trouble come vpon vs. Pharo</hi> that deſtroyed <note place="margin">Exod. 1. 16.</note> the males of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was himſelfe with all his chiual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie drowned in the Red Sea. <hi>Diues</hi> that denyed the <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 28.</note> poore beggar a crumme of bread, was himſelfe denyed a <note place="margin">Luc. 16. 21.</note> drop of water to coole his tongue in Hels tormenting <note place="margin">Verſe 24. 25, 26.</note> flames. <hi>Negauit micam: Negatur ei &amp; gutta,</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed a crumme of bread; he is denyed a drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>There ſhall be iudgement mercileſſe to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>him that ſhewes no mercy. Adonibezek</hi> had cut off the thumbes and great toes of 70 Kings; and had himſelfe <note place="margin">Iudg. 1. 7.</note> at laſt his owne thumbes and toes cut off. <hi>As I haue done, ſo God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath rewarded me.</hi> Verſe 7.</p>
               <p>Here may the Miniſter learne to winne Wolues with le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> not to diſhearten Sheepe with cruelty. <hi>With all humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde, and meekneſſe, with long ſuffering, ſupporting one</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>another through loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15170:13"/>
Here may ye Magiſtrates learne, 1. <hi>Vt ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Conſentientes</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>ſitis malis, vt approbetis:</hi> Neither doing ill your ſelues, nor <note place="margin">Aug. de verbis dom.</note> conſenting to others ill doing; for the thiefe and the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the periurer and the procurer, the vſurer and the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, the whore and the baud, ill doing, and conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 31.</note> to ill doing, are equally ill. 2. <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Negligentes vt non arguatis.</hi> Careleſſe of your owne duties, or winking at the faults of others. For, <hi>Curſed is hee that doth the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 48. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>worke of the Lord negligently.</hi> 3. <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Superbientes vt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultanter arguatis.</hi> Nor glorying in your authority, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting ouer miſery. <hi>Improue, rebuke, exhort, and diſcharge</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the duty of your calling.</hi> But how? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>with all long ſuffering and doctrine. Regat diſciplina vigor</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. in moral. l.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Manſuetudinem; &amp; manſuetudo ornet vigorem.</hi> Let Iuſtice be the rule of mercy, and mercy the crowne of Iuſtice. Be as <hi>Moſes,</hi> Meeke. But therewithall faithfull. As <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Num. 12. 3.</note> affable. But <hi>Iuſt</hi> alſo, gathering like good Shepheards the <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 2.</note> ſheepe into the fold: but reclaiming like good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates <note place="margin">Ioſh. 7. 19.</note> the Wolues from their cruelty, or vs from them. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>25</label> 
                  <hi>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the middeſt of Wolues.</head>
               <p>The heate of the female, worries the males with deſire after her: but when wearineſſe hath lulled them aſleepe, and ſleepe giuen reſpite to deſire, ſhee ſingleth out one, and away they goe; the reſt follow dry-foote; and if they light vpon him, they teare him lim-meale.</p>
               <p>When tyrants haue their will, others as wicked, and as <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> very Tyrants as themſelues, are ready to eate them; like dogges that teare one another, or Canibals that eate one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, or fiſh that deuoure one another. <hi>Minorum perditio, maiorum cibus &amp; vita.</hi> The leſſer alwayes becomming food <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Polyb. l.</hi> 15.</note> to the greater, and the ſtronger preuailing againſt the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. Like the times of <hi>Galba, Otho,</hi> and <hi>Vitellius:</hi> when Lawes <note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> lay aſleepe, and all things were adiudged by the Sword, when nothing was leſſe ſecure then to be ſecurely innocent. The imperiall Houſe of the <hi>Caeſars</hi> receiued foure Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors <note place="margin">Plut. Galb.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15170:14"/>
in leſſe then ten moneths: for one murthered another, and him firſt, that firſt corrupted the Souldiers, in teaching them to make gaine by change of Emperors.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Torua leaena lupum ſequitur: lupus ipſe capellam: <note place="margin">Virg. eglog.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Florentem cytiſum ſequitur laſciua capella.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A ſhrewd Crow hath hatcht as ſhrewd an egge. As is the Mother, ſo is the Daughter. <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 44.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A warning for vs, not to repine at the wicked. <hi>Fret not thy ſelfe becauſe of the vngodly; neither bee thou enuious</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>againſt the euill doers.</hi> It will not be long before venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance <note place="margin">Pſal 37. 1.</note> ouertake them: <hi>For they ſhall ſoone be cut downe like the graſſe; and be withered euen as the greene herbe.</hi> They <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> flouriſh for a while, but it is but a lightning before death; the rooting out of themſelues and their poſterity for euer. <hi>I my ſelfe haue ſeene the vngodly in great proſperity, and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>36</label> 
                  <hi>like a greene bay tree; and I went by and he was gone, I ſought</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>37</label> 
                  <hi>him, but his place could no where be found. The bloud-thirſty and deceitfull men ſhall not liue out halfe their dayes.</hi> Pſal. 55. 25. For either Iuſtice by the Law, or others as wicked as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues without Law, cuts them off before their time. Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is an <hi>Iſmael,</hi> whoſe hand is againſt euery man, and euery mans hand againſt him. As <hi>Actaeon</hi> was torne in peeces of his owne dogges, ſo is ſinne perſecuted of its owne Family; <note place="margin">Ouid. metam.</note> one thiefe robbes another, one adulterer is iealous of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <note place="margin">Heſiod.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clodius accuſat Maechos: Catilina Cethegum.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iauen.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>One thiefe robbes another, and the great theeues lead <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Laert. l</hi> 6.</note> the little theeues to hanging: one Adulterer is iealous of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and the more he preuailes againſt his corriuall, the deeper is he engaged to ſinne and Satan.</p>
               <q>Suis &amp; ipſa Roma viribus ruit.</q>
               <p>It falles by its owne weapons, like <hi>Saul.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31. 4. It growes deſperate, and becomes its owne executioner, like
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15170:14"/>
                  <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 23. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 5. A cruel life hath a deſperate end. <hi>Tigellinus</hi> put off his comming <note place="margin">Plut. in vit. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho.</note> before <hi>Otho</hi> as long as he could, but when excuſes could ſerue no longer, he tooke a razor and cut his owne throat: for it is a fearefull thing when malice is condemned by her <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sap.</hi> 17. 10.</note> owne teſtimony: and a Conſcience that is touched, doth euer fore-caſt cruell things. <hi>Conſcientia mala bene ſperare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>non poteſt:</hi> A cruell life cannot hope for a peaceable end. <hi>Tigellinus</hi> conſcience told him, that he had beene ſuch <note place="margin">Plut. ſupra.</note> a Wolfe vnder <hi>Nero,</hi> and ſuch a Foxe vnder <hi>Galba,</hi> that <hi>Otho</hi> to ſatisfie the State, could doe no leſſe then pull his skinne ouer his eares.</p>
               <p>Oh that, terror of Conſcience, preſent or future iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> in body or in ſoule, or in both here for a time, or in hell for euer, could reclaime men from being Wolues, and <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 18.</note> perſwade them to liue peaceably one with another, and to <note place="margin">Math. 7. 12.</note> doe as they would be done vnto!</p>
               <p>Oh that the ſweete of mutuall well-wiſhing, one man to another, by which one man becomes as a God vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; O that preſent or future bleſſings, in body, or in ſoule, or in both; here for a time, or in Heauen for euer, could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Wolues into Sheepe: Men into Doues: Gods owne <note place="margin">Pſal. 100. 2.</note> people, and <hi>Sheepe of his paſture:</hi> His Siſters, his Loues, his <note place="margin">Cant. 5. 2.</note> Doues, his vndefiled! Simplicity ſhould no longer ſuffer vnder tyranny, nor innocency vnder malice; the Sheepe vnder the teeth of the Wolfe, nor the Doue vnder the tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of the Hawke: but till theſe be perſwaded to forbeare, Sheepe and Doues muſt either fly their prouoking, or beare their cruelty.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15170:15"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON Vpon that great Embaſsie of our Lord IESVS CHRIST, recorded by his Euangeliſt Saint <hi>Matthew. Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Verſe</hi> 16.</head>
            <q>
               <l>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe in the middeſt of Wolues.</l>
               <l>Be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doues.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold, I ſend you as Sheepe in the middeſt of Wolues.</hi> A dangerous meſſage; <hi>Be therefore wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doues.</hi> Ye cannot walke ſafely, except ye walke wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily: <hi>Be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent as Doues.</hi> Wiſe as Serpents, to keepe you ſafe from Wolues: Innocent as Doues, to keepe you blameleſſe with God. He telles them not in what point this wiſedome, this innocency of theirs doth conſiſt; but ſends them as it were to Schoole, where to learne both; the one of Serpents, the other of Doues. <hi>Elegans eſt icon: mira</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Marl. in hunc locum.</note> 
               <hi>hypotypoſis.</hi> A dainty compariſon, a rare reſemblance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold, I ſend you as Sheepe in the middeſt of Wolues: Be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doues. Facilior cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eſt, vbi manifeſta formido eſt:</hi> Prouident men are ſeldomeſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. de ſimpl prclat. tr.</hi> 3.</note> damnified. Chriſt Ieſus forewarnes his Apoſtles of enſuing danger, to make them the more circumſpect to preuent it.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15170:15"/>
In the 30 verſe, he oppoſeth Flight againſt Perſecution; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man ſhould thruſt himſelfe into needleſſe danger. Here he expoſeth them as Sheepe in the midſt of Wolues: Where becauſe their Miſſion is their danger; he therefore maketh their Inſtruction their policy.</p>
            <p>When we cannot doe our duty without danger, we muſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> notwithſtanding doe it, and preuent the danger as well as we may. <hi>Gird thy loynes, and take this boxe of Oyle in thy hand,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Reg. 9. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and get thee to Ramoth Gilead: And when thou commeſt thither,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>looke where is</hi> Iehu <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Iehoſaphat, <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhi; <hi>and goe and make him ariſe vp from among his brethren, and leade him into a ſecret Chamber: Then take the boxe of Oyle, and</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>powre it on his head, and ſay; Thus ſaith the Lord, I haue annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee for King ouer Iſrael: Then open the doore, and fly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any tarrying. Eliſha</hi> commanded, and the iunior Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſingles out <hi>Iehu</hi> from the other Captaines, leaſt hee ſhould be circumuented in the doing of what he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: He flees ſo ſoone as he hath done, leaſt he ſhould be apprehended for the doing. If the duty of our calling expoſe vs vnto neceſſary danger, and wee dye for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences (as <hi>Iohn</hi> for reprouing <hi>Herod,)</hi> our death is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious: <note place="margin">Math. 14. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Right deare in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Saints.</hi> If we eſcape (as <hi>Eliah</hi> out of the hands of <hi>Iezabel,)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Reg. 19 2.</note> our life is honourable. <hi>Triumphat Victor imperator, &amp; non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Confeſſ. l.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>viciſſet niſi pugnaſſet:</hi> The Conqueror returnes triumphant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but had he not conquered, he had not triumphed; and had he not fought, he had not conquered: <hi>&amp; quanto maius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>periculum fuit in pralio; tanto maius gaudium in triumpho:</hi> The greater the danger was in the fight, the greater by ſo much is the glory in the triumph. <hi>Horatius Cocles</hi> ſtood ſingle <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liu. decad.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2.</note> againſt <hi>Porſennas</hi> whole Army, till the bridge was broken behind him: then he leapt into the water, and ſaued himſelfe by ſwimming: His firſt care was to performe his duty to his Countrey; his next care was to reſerue himſelfe for his Countrey.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot at once performe all duties wee owe to Church and Common-wealth: <hi>Dauid</hi> did his Father <hi>Ieſſe</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15170:16"/>
good ſeruice, when being his Shepheard, and but a ſtripling, <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17. 34.</note> hee ſlew the Lyon and the Beare, and reſcued his Sheepe. He did his Maſter <hi>Saul</hi> better ſeruice, when his Captaine and a man, hee ſlew his ten for the others one. <hi>Saul hath killed his thouſand, and Dauid his ten thouſand:</hi> but the <note place="margin">Cap. 18. 7.</note> beſt ſeruice he euer did, was Gods and his Countries; when an old man and a King, when hee fed <hi>Iacob,</hi> Gods people, <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 72.</note> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his inheritance: when hee fed them with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>73</label> and true heart, and guided them prudently in all his wayes.</p>
            <p>To teach vs to walke warily betweene deſpaire and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Neither with the <hi>Circumciliones</hi> to force men to kill <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. contra lit. Petiliani, lib</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 83.</note> vs, through a vaine hope to become Martyrs; <hi>Martyrem non facit poena ſed cauſa:</hi> It is not the paine, but the cauſe that makes a Martyr; nor yet with the Stoicks preſume of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. cont. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 47.</note> through opinion of fatall neceſſity. <hi>Nuſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuta fides;</hi> A man knowes not whom to truſt: Therefore it is, that our bleſſed Sauiour in the next verſe, bids vs, <hi>Beware of men. Ye are,</hi> in the Text, <hi>as Sheepe in the middeſt of Wolues; Be ye</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 17.</note> 
               <hi>therefore wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Creatures ſerue man foure manner of wayes, 1. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de Gen. ad Lit. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>vtiliter Probando,</hi> Demonſtratiuely for our good, as the Angels; 1. to direct <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the way: 2. to comfort <hi>Eliah</hi> with bread and water; and <hi>Hagar,</hi> with ſhewing her a well. <note place="margin">Exod. 13. 21. 1 Reg. 19. 6.</note> 3. To protect the Iſraelites from the Aegyptians; <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21. 19.</note> with the Sword; <hi>Eliſha</hi> with Horſes and Chariots of fire. <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 19.</note> 4. To deliuer the Apoſtles out of priſon. 5. To reioyce at, <note place="margin">Ioſh. 5. 13. 2 Reg. 6. 17.</note> and aſſiſt our well doing, our conuerſion; our prayers. 6. To take charge ouer vs while we be aliue. 7. To carry <note place="margin">Acts 5. 17.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.</note> vs to Heauen when wee be dead. The ſecond vſe of the <note place="margin">Apoc. 8. 3.</note> Creature is, <hi>Poenaliter Laedendo;</hi> Exemplarly to puniſh, as the <note place="margin">Pſal 91. 11.</note> fiery Serpents in the Wilderneſſe, the Diuels in Hell. The <note place="margin">Luc. 16. 20.</note> third ſeruice that the Creature doth vnto man, is <hi>i. Salubriter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num 11. 6.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 16. 23.</note> 
               <hi>exercendo,</hi> naturally to vſe, Some for foode, as the cleane beaſt, 2. Some for rayment, as the Sheepe, 3. Some for <note place="margin">Leuit. 11. 47.</note> phyſicke, <hi>applicando naturalia actiua paſſiuis,</hi> by applying naturall cauſes to produce naturall effects. 4. Some for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15170:16"/>
as the Elements without vs, and without which we cannot liue one minute: or within vs, and whereof we are compoſed, and without which we are not. 5. Some for pleaſure, as <hi>Saul</hi> his Houſe and Wiues, the Kingdomes of <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> and of <hi>Iudah</hi> giuen to <hi>Dauid.</hi> The fourth kind of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that man hath of the Creature, is <hi>Ignoranter docendo,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing him by the inſtinct of Nature, either <hi>ad ſtudium Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiae,</hi> To enrich his vnderſtanding with wiſedome, as the Serpent, or, <hi>ad Comparandam exercendam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> virtutem,</hi> To crowne his actions with morall vertues, as the Doue: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo naught, but is good for ſomething. The Spider gathereth the infected ayre; the Toade affoords a ſtone precious for the ſight: The Viper on <hi>Pauls</hi> hand, proues <note place="margin">Acts 28. 3.</note> him an Apoſtle, not a murtherer. <hi>Behold, I giue vnto you power to tread on Serpents, and Scorpions, and ouer all the power</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 10. 19.</note> 
               <hi>of the Enemy, and nothing ſhall hurt you:</hi> The Angels that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the old World that repented not, are enſamples how <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 4.</note> we fall from grace, or remaine impenitent after warning. The Serpent that deceiued vs in Paradice, where was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to offend vs, teacheth vs in my Text to walke warily in the World, where are Wolues to deuoure vs.</p>
            <p>Men may goe to Schoole, and learne euen of brute <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> beaſts. The Piſmire prepares in Summer againſt Winter. <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 7.</note> The Riuer-Horſe finding himſelfe ouer-groſſe, by reaſon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. biſt. nat. l.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note> of his high feeding, ſets his body againſt the ſharpeſt reede hee can meete with, and ſo pricketh a vaine in his legge, and letteth himſelfe bloud. The Hart drawes arrowes out <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> of his body, by eating of the hearbe <hi>Dictamnus.</hi> The Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards eate of the hearbe <hi>Calaminth,</hi> and it is their antidote againſt the byting of Serpents. The Land <hi>Torteyſe</hi> prepares himſelfe with <hi>Marioram</hi> againſt he fights with them. The Swallowes cure the ſoare eyes of their young ones with <hi>Celedine.</hi> The Dragon his ſqueazy ſtomacke with Lectuce. The Stocke-Doues, Iayes, Merles, Owſels, with bay-berrias: Partridges, Houſe-Doues, and Turtle-Doues, with Pelleta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the wall; all water Fowle with Cicory. If the Swine hath eaten of the hearbe Hyoſciamus, he taketh Creafiſhes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15170:17"/>
and it is his antidote: wilde Oliues the Elephants after the ſwallowing of the Lyzard Camelion; and Piſmires the Beares, after Mandrake Apples. Finally, the Snake by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe, and lying ſtill all Winter, hath a certaine membrane or filme growen ouer his whole body; but hauing recourſe to Fenell, with the iuyce thereof, hee caſteth that old coate that clogged him, and appeareth freſh, ſlicke, and young againe.</p>
            <p>O that the painfull Piſmire could ſet ſluggards on worke, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> or that the Apoſtles Law were better obſerued, <hi>that he that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 5. 10.</note> 
               <hi>would not worke, ſhould not eate.</hi> O that we that are more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to ſinne, then the <hi>Hyppopotamus</hi> to diſeaſes, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to eaſe our ſelues of our corrupt affections, as he of his ſuperfluous humors. O that we ſought remedy to cure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall concupiſcence, as the Hart after <hi>Dictamnus,</hi> to draw darts out of his wounds. O that wee armed our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne and Satan with the armour of righteouſneſſe, as the Camelyon with Calamynth, or the Tortoyſe with Marioram againſt Serpents. O that we applyed to our ſick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoules the comfort of Gods Word, as the Swallowes Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, to their ſore eyes; and digeſted it into our ſoules and conſciences, as the Dragon Lectuce into his ſtomacke; the Birds Pellitory, or the Fowles Cicory. But we alas are more filthy then Swine, and yet wallow ſtill in the myre of ſinne: wee haue ſwallowed more ſinnes, then the Elephant Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards; and yet neuer ſeeke after oyle of mercy to purchaſe pardon. Surcharged with a lethargy of ſinne, ſecureleſſe euer to be awaked, waxen old in ſinne, and yet without ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to be renewed by grace.</p>
            <p>See, oh ſee how wee are ſent to Schoole to brute beaſts, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> and to learne of them; and that not onely the Theoricke of Contemplation, but the Practicke alſo of morall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. <hi>The Oxe knoweth his Owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Crib: but Iſrael hath not knowen, my people hath not vnderſtood.</hi> The olde Pellican pierceth her breaſt to feede her young: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. hiſt. nat. l.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> The young Storkes feede the olde, that formerly fed them: But Parents are growen vnnaturall, and Children vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15170:17"/>
The Elephants know that they are hunted for their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 30</note> teeth, and in extreamities breake them off, as a ranſome for their liues. The Beauer bytes off his ſtones; the Sea-Calfe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> eaſts vp his gall and runnet in his maw: O let vs alſo caſt away euery thing that preſſeth downe, and the ſinne that hangeth ſo faſt on. <hi>Let vs runne with patience the race that is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſet before vs. Mahomet</hi> the great Turke diſcontinued the <note place="margin">Hiſt. Turc.</note> warres two yeeres to accompany his faire <hi>Irene;</hi> for which, when his Baſſoes muttered, he vpon an appointed day, led her forth into the great Hall of his Pallace, arrayed in the moſt richeſt robes of ſtate, and Iewels for price and worth the moſt precious that the whole perephery of his Empire affoorded, to the approbation of his choyce, and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full amazement of the beholders; not in regard of her bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery alone, but much more of her ſurpaſſing beauty: but he with the one hand tooke hold of the haire of her head, and with his ſemitary in the other hand ſmote off her head. An action for murdering of an Innocent, and his loue Turkiſh, and like himſelfe; but for reſolution from vaine pleaſure ſingular, and ſuch, that had God beene the obiect, and the ſacrifice vnbloudy, <hi>Iuberem macte virtute,</hi> As <hi>Porſenna</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liu. dec.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> ſometimes ſpake to <hi>Cain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mutius,</hi> and could not but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and admire. Better things are expected from vs, then from bruit Beaſts and Infidels great ſhame it were for vs to come ſhort of them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>From diuers Creatures men learne diuers things. Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">Aelian. var. hiſt.</note> from the Spyder; the ordering of a battell from the Crane; Nauigation from the Kyte: and in my Text, ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city from the Sheepe, innocency from the Doue, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from the Serpent; and that in a foure-fold reſpect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He refuſeth to heare the voyce of the Charmer, charme he</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Serpents property.</note> 
                  <hi>neuer ſo wiſely.</hi> He holdeth, ſaith <hi>Iunius</hi> (out of <hi>Ierome, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Caſſiodere,</hi> &amp;c.) one eare cloſe to the ground, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">1. Pſal. 58. 5. <hi>In hunc locum.</hi>
                  </note> the other with his tayle.</p>
               <p>A leſſon for vs all, an embleme in ſtead of a Doctrine; to <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15170:18"/>
                  <hi>Take heede how we heare.</hi> The eare is the Organ of Faith. <note place="margin">Luc. 8. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>For Faith comes by hearing: He that hath eares to heare, let</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>him heare.</hi> We muſt of neceſſity heare; but we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 9.</note> take heede how we heare. <hi>The Sower went forth to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 8. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſow his ſeede; and as he ſowed, ſome fell by the way ſide, and it was troden vnder feete; and the Fowles of Heauen deuoured it vp: and ſome fell among ſtones, and when it was ſprung vp, it withered</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>away, becauſe it wanted moiſtneſſe; and ſome fell among thornes, and the thornes ſprang vp with it, and choaked it: and ſome fell</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>on good ground, and ſprang vp, and bare fruit an hundred fold.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> The ſeede is, <hi>the Word.</hi> The good ground, are they that with an honeſt and good heart, <hi>heare the Word, and keepe it,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>11</label> 
                  <hi>and bring forth fruit with patience;</hi> Such a one, <hi>Libenter audit</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>15</label> 
                  <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilia; Prudender diſcernit audita; Obedienter operatur intellecta:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern. epiſt.</note> He is willing to heare what makes for his good; like <hi>Mary,</hi> that ſate at Ieſus feete, and heard his preaching. He <note place="margin">Luc. 10. 39.</note> is of vnderſtanding to iudge of what he heareth, like the Apoſtles, to whom it was giuen to vnderſtand the ſecrets <note place="margin">Luc. 8. 10.</note> of the Kingdome of God; Is conformable in life, according to his knowledge; like <hi>Iames,</hi> and all true beleeuers <hi>ſheweth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>his faith by his workes;</hi> and liueth as he beleeueth.</p>
               <p>A Caueat for Magiſtrates how they heare either open <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> flatteries, or priuate accuſations. Two men had a Cauſe in Iſſue before <hi>Ariſtides;</hi> the one to aduantage his owne <note place="margin">Plut. Ariſtid.</note> cauſe, and diſaduantage his enemies, told him; This fellow my aduerſary, hath done you great wrong: My friend (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Ariſtides)</hi> tell me onely the wrong that he hath done thee; for I am Iudge here to doe thee right, not my ſelfe. He would not ſuffer the one to get the ſtart of the other, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by inſinuating himſelfe into the fauour of the Iudge, or by by-accuſing of his aduerſary. <hi>Alexanders</hi> manner of <note place="margin">Plut. Alex.</note> ſitting in iudgement, is this Doctrines embleme: for he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on his elbow, with his hand vnder his head, whileſt that the Plaintiffes Bill was in reading; and ſo lent one eare to the plaintiffe, and reſerued the other for the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. For,</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15170:18"/>
                  <l>Quiſtatuerit aliquid parte inaudita altera: <note place="margin">Sen. Med.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Aequum licet ſtatuerit, haud aequus eſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>He that determines a Controuerſie without hearing of both parties, though happily his iudgement chance to be iuſt, yet is he himſelfe an vniuſt Iudge. The Law of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity muſt haue its courſe: becauſe. <hi>Innocens ſi accuſatus ſit, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolui poteſt;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cic. pro Roſcio.</note> 
                  <hi>nocens niſi accuſatus fuerit, damnari non poteſt.</hi> An honeſt man may come to his tryall, and be acquitted; a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor vnleſſe he be arraigned, cannot be conuicted.</p>
               <p>But that which in a generall vſe concernes vs all as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> is, That as <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> when he was to paſſe by the Syrens, <note place="margin">Homer.</note> ſtopped the eares of them that were with him in the Ship, and bound himſelfe to the maine maſt; and as Serpents <note place="margin">Plin.</note> ſtoppe their eares againſt the Mathematician ſpelles: ſo we, <hi>ad patriam feſtinantes mortiferos Syrenarum cantus, ſurda aure</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hier.</note> 
                  <hi>tranſire debemus:</hi> as we haſten to our Countrey of Heauen, ſhould turne the deafe eare to the entiſing vanities in our iourney. And this is one point of wiſedome that we may learne of the Serpent, in ſtopping the eare; another is in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the head:</p>
               <p>For howſoeuer the reſt of the body ſpeedes, he will be ſure to keepe the head.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer alteration in Religion, innouation in State, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> occurrance betweene man and man may happen; it is our part and duty to preſerue faith towards GOD, fidelity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Countrey, good report among men, conſcience in all our actions, <hi>I haue fought a good fight, and haue finiſhed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>my courſe; I haue kept the Faith. I haue fought a good fight;</hi> not onely with Beaſts, after the manner of men: not onely againſt fleſh and bloud, <hi>but againſt Principalities, againſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Powers, and againſt worldly Gouernours, the Princes of the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this World, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes. I haue fought</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, the race that is ſet before me; looking vnto Ieſus Chriſt the author and finiſher of my faith.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the Faith;</hi> the <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> laid vp like the <hi>Vrim</hi> and the <hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6 20.</note> on the breaſt, without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15170:19"/>
God. Whatſoeuer alteration in Religion, innouation in State, occurrance betweene man and man may happen, it is our part and duty to preſerue faith towards God. 2. Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity towards our Countrey. <hi>God forbid that I ſhould ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord, and ceaſe praying for you.</hi> The people had caſt off <hi>Samuel,</hi> and not onely him, but the Lord alſo from <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8. 7.</note> raigning ouer them; yet it had beene ſinne in him not to preſerue fidelity towards his Countrey, or to haue ceaſed praying for them. As <hi>Phocion</hi> was led to execution, one <note place="margin">Plut. Phoe.</note> asked him what he would haue to his ſonne? nothing ſaid he, but that my ſonne remember not the wrong that my Countrey now doth vnto me. In all occurrances we muſt preſerue faith towards God, fidelity towards our Countrey. 3. Good report among men, <hi>that when they ſpeake euill of you, as of euill doers, they may be aſhamed, which blame your good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>in Chriſt. Duo ſunt tibi neceſſaria, Conſcientia &amp; fama: Conſcientia propter Deum, fama propter Proximum.</hi> A <note place="margin">Ambr. epiſt. ad Conſtant.</note> man muſt be tender of his Conſcience, and of his good name: Of his Conſcience, to be iuſtified before God; of his good name, to be iuſtified before men: He muſt preſerue good report among men. 4. Conſcience in all his actions. <hi>Our reioycing is this, the teſtimony of our Conſcience, that in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and godly pureneſſe, and not in fleſhly wiſedome, but by the grace of God we haue had our conuerſation in the world.</hi> How hard ſoeuer we fare in the world, this will continually feaſt vs. <hi>For a good Conſcience, is a continuall feaſt.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The neerer that the members neighboureth one vpon <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> another, the greater is their ſympathy one with another; the neerer and dearer that a man is to God, the King and his Countrey, the greater faith, fealty, and fidelity is hee to beare to God, the King, &amp; his Countrey. God hath commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated <note place="margin">Pſal. 12. 6.</note> to you his name &amp; authority; his name, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> his authority the Sword. The King hath made you his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> of Oyre, and Determine, to heare and iudge: your Countrey hath put her ſelfe into your hands, as vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer barne. You of all men muſt ſtand ſtiffe for God, the King, and your Countrey. As L. <hi>Tubero,</hi> ſometimes Lord
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15170:19"/>
Chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſate on his <hi>Pretorian</hi> Throne; one <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin hiſt. nat. l.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> of the Birds called <hi>Picus Martius,</hi> pearcht on his head, ſtayed there, notwithſtanding the concourſe of people, and ſuffered <hi>Tubero</hi> to take him downe: The South-ſayer thereupon coniectured, that if the Bird were let goe, that it portended the ruine and ouerthrow of the whole State and Empire; but if that he were killed, that then it preſaged the death of the ſaid Lord Chiefe Iuſtice. Did not <hi>Tubero</hi> now hold the Wolfe by the eares? If he holds him, he bytes him; if he lets him goe, he killes him: but he was not long in deliberating whether to preferre his owne, or his Countries good; and incontinently pulled the Bird in pieces. And it was not long till the preſage of the Bird tooke effect indeed, and was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in <hi>Tuberos</hi> owne perſon. He was not like <hi>Caligula,</hi> that <note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> wiſhed that all the Senators had but one necke, that hee might cut it off at a blow. Nor like <hi>Nero,</hi> that therefore <note place="margin">Xiphilmus in Nerone.</note> thought <hi>Priamus</hi> a happy man; for that hee ſaw together with himſelfe the ioynt deſtruction of himſelfe and his Countrey together. <hi>Tubero</hi> in prophane learning, and the Serpent in Diuine, be better Schoolemaſters: The one thought it better, <hi>vt Pereat vnus quàm vnitas:</hi> Rather as <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 11. 50.</note> prophecyed, that one man dye for the people, then that the whole Nation ſhould periſh: The other, howſoeuer the body ſpeedes, will be ſure to keepe the head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Notum eſt, eum totum corpus pro capite obijcere ferientibus.</hi> It <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> is remarkable in the Serpent, that he interpoſeth the whole <note place="margin">Aug. de doct.</note> body a fence for his head; ſo ſhould wee <hi>pro capite noſtro</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſtiana, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Christo, corpus potius perſequentibus offerre:</hi> Rather take the <note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> blow our ſelues, then that it ſhould light vpon our head, Chriſt Ieſus. The Serpent ſlippes away if he can; if hee cannot, yet <hi>Caput ab ictu ſubtrahit: cedi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> partem reliquam derelinquit;</hi> Howſoeuer the body ſpeedes, he is ſure to keepe the head. To teach vs, ſaith <hi>Hilary, noſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hoc exemplo oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hil. in Malt.</note> 
                  <hi>ſi quid acciderit perſecutionum caput noſtrum quod eſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus occulere, vt ablatis nobis in omnes cruciatus, fidem ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitam, iactura Corporis communiamus:</hi> To interpoſe our bodies for the defence of our head; <hi>to ſuffer</hi> (as the Apoſtle
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15170:20"/>
counſelleth) <hi>afflictions, as good Souldiers of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 3.</note> rather as <hi>Peter</hi> promiſed; and wee all are bound to make good, <hi>to dye for him, then deny him.</hi> And this is to be wiſe as <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 35.</note> Serpents, in keeping the head. The third remarkable thing in the Serpent, for vs to imitate; is, that,</p>
               <p>Euery Spring he caſteth his olde coat; he beginnes at the <note place="margin">The third pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty.</note> head, and turnes the skinne ouer it. All that will be good Chriſtians, muſt according to the Apoſtle, <hi>Caſt off the olde</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 8. <hi>ea.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>man, which is corrupt through deceiueable luſts; and put on the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>new man, who after God is created in holineſſe and true righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If any man will be in Chriſt, let him be a new Creature.</hi> In <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17.</note> Baptiſme we firſt contract it; in the Sacrament of the Altar we renew it, daily we make profeſſion of it, and here in my Text, are we ſent to Schoole, to the Serpent to practice it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Per cauer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a anguſtias cearctatus depoſita veteri tunica vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>nouas accipere dicitur:</hi> He paſſeth through a narrow <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de doct. Chriſtiana, l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> place, and ſo leaues his skinne behind him. <hi>Sic exuendus eſt à nobis vetus homo, vt induamur nouo:</hi> So muſt we caſt off the old man, and put on the new. <note place="margin">Aug. ſup.</note>
               </p>
               <p>More particularly, and to intimate the preſent occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> whomſoeuer either ſeruice to the King, or Countrey, or occaſion for himſelfe or others, haue ſummoned to this Aſſiles, let him remember to leaue his old coat behind him. Let your hearts (ye reuerend Iudges) be as raced Tables, without reſpect of perſons; For, <hi>iniquus eſt index qui ant inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cic. pro Roſcio.</note> 
                  <hi>aut fauet:</hi> Neither fauour, nor disfauour, can ſtand with the equity of a Iudge. Yours, all the reſt, deuoid of all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, to receiue the ſtampe of Iuſtice, that you Maſter Sheriffe hang not an innocent for his goods; nor you of the Iury, acquit a Malefactor for his friends; nor you the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace, looke on to giue ayme. <hi>Ye may neither</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>iuſtifie the wicked, nor condemne the iuſt; for that is abhomination.</hi> Ye may not as newters ſtand aloofe, and looke on, like <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Albanus</hi> betweene the Romans and the Fidenates: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t igitur</hi> (ſuch was the forme of <hi>Tullus</hi> iudgement vpon him) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liu. decad.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>paulo ante aninium inter fidenatem Romanam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>rem, ancipitem geſſiſti: ita iam corpus paſſion diſtrabendum dabis.</hi> As thy
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15170:20"/>
minde but a little ſince was wauering, ſo ſhall now thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be diſtracted betweene the enemy and vs; and thereupon was incontinently faſtened to two Chariots and ſo rent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder in the middeſt. And as for the proſecutor and the witneſſes, let the firſt take heede that malice ſet him not a worke againſt conſcience, like <hi>Theophilus,</hi> who perſecuted <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat hiſt, eccle. l.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 7.</note> his owne faith, and turned Anthropomorphit; ſo to vent his ſpleene on <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hermopolis.</hi> Let the reſt beware leaſt in befriending their friend, they make God their enemy: like <hi>Scipio</hi> his Army, that ſided contrary ſides; the Nauy with <hi>Sex. Digitius;</hi> the Campe with <hi>Q. Trebellius,</hi> ready ſaith <hi>Lalius,</hi> to ſweare, <hi>Magis quae vellent, quàm quae</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liu. dec.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſciant vera eſſe,</hi> Rather what they would haue, then what they knew to be true. The one is, <hi>the taking of Gods Name in vaine, for which GOD will not hold a man guiltleſſe:</hi> The <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 7.</note> other is, <hi>the finne againſt the holy Ghoſt; it will neuer be forgiuen.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 12 32.</note> Learne therefore of the Serpent, to caſt off your old coat, to leaue your old acquaintance at home, and to come hither vnpreiudicated in affection, either of loue or hatred, like ſo many <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> whom in caſe of Iuſtice, neither friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <note place="margin">Plut. Ariſtid.</note> could make to ſtep aſide for his friend, nor enuy moue to doe vniuſtice to his very enemy. And this is to be wiſe as Serpents, in caſting off the old coat.</p>
               <p>Finally, before he coupleth with the Lamprey, he diſgor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <note place="margin">The 4. proper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie.</note> himſelfe of his poyſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> out of <hi>Macer</hi> obſerueth, that the Lampreyes be all <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. nat. l</hi> 32. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> female, and couple with Serpents.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Serpenti nubit, promptè<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex aequore ſaltat in littus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenius</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De aquatilibus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> out of <hi>Oppianus.</hi> But before they come together, he caſteth his poyſon, as the Emblamiſts note, and make it <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Andr. Alciat emblem.</hi> 191.</note> an hieroglyphicke of marriage. Whence the naturall Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, the Moraliſt, and Diuine, obſerue each of them their reſpectiue Doctrine: The firſt is Naturall, the ſecond Morall, the third Theologicall.</p>
               <p>Man and Woman before they be made one by Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doctrine</hi> 1.</note> muſt forgoe all ſiniſter opinion, that the one might haue of the other; and take one the other, for better, for worſe:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15170:21"/>
for richer, for poorer. The Magiſtrate, for as much as he is <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> the Husband of the Countrey, before he intermeddles with her, muſt purge himſelfe of all things, that may hinder his common peace with her: If any formerly hath offered any hard meaſure vnto him, he may not now take aduantage of his place, to reuenge it.</p>
               <p>For as much as the communion of Saints, by the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> of the Sacraments, incorporates the members of Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>To be members one of another;</hi> we may <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 5.</note> not preſume to communicate in the Sacraments, till wee haue purged our ſelues of the leauen of maliciouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Art thou a married man? learne here to liue peaceably <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> with thy Wife. <hi>Shee is fleſh of thy fleſh, and bone of thy bone.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2 23.</note> And <hi>neuer any man hated his owne fleſh.</hi> Shee cannot lightly <note place="margin">Gal 5. 29.</note> be a veryer Vixen then <hi>Xantippe;</hi> yet <hi>Socrates,</hi> a Heathen, learnt to beare, not onely with her thunder, but with her tempeſt alſo, raine, and ſhowes.</p>
               <p>And are not you, ye reuerend Fathers, as <hi>Moſes</hi> brazen <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Serpent, without venome, curing your beholders of the venome of Serpents? Are any ſlung of Serpents? where <note place="margin">Num. 21. 9.</note> doe they looke but vpon you? Are any circumuented by their fraud, or oppreſſed by their malice? whither doe they come but to you? <hi>Index &amp; ara idem ſunt: pariter enim ad</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
                  <hi>vtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> confugium.</hi> The Iudge and the Altar are morally the ſame: for where but with you ſhall a man finde San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary?</p>
               <p>Finally, come you my Brethren to communicate in the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> myſteries of your ſaluation? <hi>If thou bring thy gift to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>and there remember that thy brother hath ought againſt thee; leaue there thine offering before the Altar, and goe thy way:</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>24</label> 
                  <hi>firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</hi> There is no liuing in <hi>Ireland</hi> for any thing that hath ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome; there is no coupling with the Lamprey with the poyſon: there is no comming to the Lords Table, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of your naturall corruptions, and foſtering of them; you muſt caſt off, you moſt caſt vp your old coates, your innated venome: you muſt firſt be reconciled to God, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15170:21"/>
your Brethren. Firſt, waſh your hands, before you eate: <hi>Waſh them in Innocency; and ſo goe to the Lords Altar. Behold,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 26. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſend you as Sheepe in the middeſt of Wolues: be ye therefore wiſe at Serpents, and innocent as Doues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non multum diſtat in vitio aut decipere aut decipi poſſe:</hi> It is <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic.</note> incident to man to deceiue, and to be deceiued. To preuent both, our bleſſed Sauiour counſelleth in my Text; <hi>To be wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doues.</hi> Innocent as Doues: <hi>Ne</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hieron ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>cuiquam machineris dolos;</hi> Wiſe as Serpents: <hi>Ne aliorum ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planteris inſidijs;</hi> Neither deceiuing, nor being deceiued. If either goe ſingle, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>a Soli.</hi> Woe vnto him that is alone; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <note place="margin">Eccleſ 4. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Prudentia abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſimplicitate malitia eſt: &amp; ſimplicitas ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ſup. Oſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</note> 
                  <hi>ratione ſtultitia eſt.</hi> Wiſedome without Innocency, is but machauillian policy without Religion: and Innocency without wiſedome, but will-worſhip without knowledge. The Serpent had wiſedome without innocency, and became <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 1.</note> a Tempter: <hi>Eue</hi> had innocency without wiſedome, and <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 6.</note> became a tranſgreſſor. <hi>Vtra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bene in admonitione conuertit:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Greg. in moral.</note> 
                  <hi>vt ſimplicitatem columba aſtutia Serpentis inſtrueret: &amp; rurſus ſerpentis aſtutiam, columbae ſimplicitas temperaret:</hi> Chriſt Ieſus ioynes both together in the Inſtruction, that Wiſedome might be Innocencies Lecturer, and Innocency Wiſedomes moderator: becauſe, <hi>vtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> per ſe indigens,</hi> (as one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes <note place="margin">Salluſt.</note> betweene plaine force and ſtratagems) <hi>alterum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius auxilio ege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Wiſedome muſt informe Innocency, and Innocency temper Wiſedome.</p>
               <p>A man may not venture on Church, or Common-wealth <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> with one ſingle vertue: The Miniſter muſt haue his head <note place="margin">Exod. 29. 6.</note> crowned like <hi>Aarons;</hi> becauſe of his ſanctity: <hi>For the Lord</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 10. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>will be ſanctified in all them that come neere vnto him.</hi> His tongue clouen, like thoſe on the Apoſtles. <hi>Propter donorum diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2. 3.</note> becauſe of his gifts: <hi>Out of his mouth, as out of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mar. ex bul.</note> 
                  <hi>Lambes, muſt goe a two edged Sword.</hi> Becauſe the Word of <note place="margin">Apoc. 1. 16.</note> God in his mouth muſt be liuely, <hi>and mighty in operation,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſharper then any two edged Sword;</hi> Edged on the one ſide, and on the other: On the one ſide, with the Vrim of the Word, on the other, with the Thummin of good life; <hi>leaſt</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15170:22"/>
                  <hi>after that he hath preached to others, he himſelfe ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 27.</note> The Magiſtrate muſt be a man of courage, <hi>fearing God, dealing truly, and hating couetouſneſſe.</hi> He muſt be a man <note place="margin">Exod. 18. 21.</note> of courage, like the title of the Kings of <hi>England; Defender of the Faith.</hi> He muſt haue the feare of God before his eyes; like the <hi>Seraphins, that couer their faces with their wings.</hi> He <note place="margin">Eſa. 6. 2.</note> muſt be iuſt and vpright in all his dealings, like <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dek: Melchi-zedek, Melchi-ſalem, King of righteouſneſſe, King</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>of peace;</hi> but firſt <hi>Melchi-zedek King of righteouſneſſe, then Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi-ſalem King of peace.</hi> He muſt be free from couetouſneſſe, he muſt be more, he muſt hate it; he muſt be free from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, <hi>contented like a good Chriſtian with what he hath.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 6.</note> He muſt be more, <hi>he muſt as a good Magiſtrate hate it, as the roote of all euill.</hi> He muſt haue <hi>Iuſtitiam in affectu,</hi> Iuſtice in <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>10</label> the will; <hi>Prudentiam in intellectu,</hi> Wiſedome in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: <hi>Fortitudinem in effectu,</hi> Fortitude in the reſolution. <note place="margin">Ambr. de officijs.</note> 
                  <hi>Temperantiam in vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Temperance in the life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What King going to make warre againſt another King, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not downe firſt, and taketh counſell, whether he be able</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>with ten thouſand men, to meete him that commeth againſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 14. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>him with twenty thouſand?</hi> Now our warfare is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt few, or contemptible, but many and mighty aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries: not Subiects, but Princes; not carnall, but ſpirituall: <hi>not againſt fleſh and bloud, but againſt Principalities, againſt Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and againſt worldly Gouernours; the Princes of the darkneſſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes. For this cauſe take</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>13</label> 
                  <hi>vnto you the whole Armour of God:</hi> The weapons offenſiue and defenſiue, <hi>the Sword of the Spirit, the Shield of Faith, the Breaſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, and the Helmet of ſaluat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>: ſtand</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>14</label> 
                  <hi>therefore and your loynes girt about with veritie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the breaſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, and your feete ſhod with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>15</label> 
                  <hi>of the Goſpell of Peace: about all, take the ſhield of Faith,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>16</label> 
                  <hi>wherewith we may quench all the fiery darts of the wicked; and</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> 
                  <hi>take the helmet of ſaluation, and the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God; Ioyne moreouer vertue with your faith, and with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>vertue Knowledge, and with knowledge Temperance: and with</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15170:22"/>
                  <hi>Temperance Patience: and with Patience, Godlineſſe, and with godlineſſe brotherly kindeneſſe: and with brotherly kindeneſſe,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Loue:</hi> Be wiſe as Serpents, but be there withall innocent as Doues; for wiſedome without innocencie is but ſubtilty: and innocencie without wiſedome, foolery. <hi>Be ye therfore wiſe as Serpents, and</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Innocent as Doues.</head>
               <p>Men, like Apes loue to imitate: for as they that would <note place="margin">Plut. Moralib.</note> be neate, conſult with their glaſſe, how things ſtand accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the idaea of their forming fancie: ſo they that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend matter of conſequence, propoſe vnto themſelues ſome man of note, how he in the like caſe carried himſelfe and <note place="margin">Plut. Moralib.</note> his cauſe. The poynt then of diſcretion, is in the choyce-making. 1. of the Obiect 2. of the Qualitie, 3. of the Exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 1. What to imitate and to be like vnto: 2. Wherein and in what reſpect: 3 How farre forth. <hi>Optimum eſt maiorum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Seneca in prouer.</note> 
                  <hi>veſtigia, ſirecte praeceſſerint,</hi> it is a very good thing to bee like vnto our anceſtors in their good parts. <hi>Scipio African</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Zunigle.</note> propoſed vnto himſelfe <hi>Cyrus Zenophon</hi> to be like vnto <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Alexander</hi> the great. And <hi>Selimus</hi> the great Turke, <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar: Diogenes,</hi> like a ſnayle, loued to carry his houſe on his backe, <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> like the Heliotropium, turned with the carte: <hi>Lyſander</hi> in the warres was both a Lyon and a Foxe: <note place="margin">Plut. Lacon.</note> The Apoſtles, in my text, Serpents &amp; Doues. The firſt point of diſcretion is in the choyce-making what to imitate and to be like vnto: the ſecond is, wherein and in what reſpect euery good man hath ſome thing in him to bee liked: but wee may not in euery thing bee like to euery good man. When <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>xis</hi> was to picture <hi>Iuno,</hi> hee choſe among all the Agrigetine beauties onely fiue: and preſented in thoſe fiue, <hi>quod erat, in vnaquaque praecipuum,</hi> that that euery one had <note place="margin">Anominus.</note> ſingular and ſurpaſſing others. When we propoſe patternes for our liues, it muſt be a <hi>plurimis optimis,</hi> a choyce of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and very good, and then are wee bound to imitate in them, <hi>Non omnia, ſed optima,</hi> not euery thing, but the beſt; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem ibidem. Cic.</hi> 7. <hi>Offic.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe, <hi>Non vinitur cum perfectis,</hi> the beſt be but men, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15170:23"/>
men haue their imperfections. The third thing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in this choice of ours, is, how farre forth to be like our patterne. Of this the Apoſtle giues the rule: <hi>Be yet</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>followers of me, euen as I am of Chriſt: In his omnibus quaec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. contra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilianum lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>in nobis bona noſtis: imitatores noſtri estote, ſicut not Chriſti:</hi> follow vs, not ſimply and without reſtraint, but with this limitation, as we follow Chriſt: but if we pretend Chriſt, and not follow Chriſt, <hi>retinete illud dominicum,</hi> let Chriſt his rule be your leſſon; <hi>The Scribes and Phariſes ſit in Moſes chaire, all therefore whatſoeuer they bid you obſerue, that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>obſerue and doe: but after their workes doe not: for they ſay and</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>doe not.</hi> The things that my text propoſeth to vs to bee like vnto, are the <hi>Serpent</hi> and the <hi>Doue:</hi> the things wherein we ſhould be like vnto them, are Wiſedome and Innocencie: how farre foorth we ſhould be like vnto them, I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> and now I come to the <hi>Doue. Behold, I ſend you as ſheepe in the middeſt of Wolues: be ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſe as Serpents</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And Innocent as Doues.</head>
               <p>Innocencie is an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, communicating her name to contrarie natures, as much as is betweene Loue and Feare; there is ſaith <hi>Bernard, Innocentia Timeris, &amp; innocentia A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> Children of a name but no kinne: the one the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Loue, the other of Feare: the one generous, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther baſe. <hi>Ioſephs</hi> vertue brought him to that honour and power, by which if he would, he might haue reuenged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on his brethren: <hi>for at his word was all Egypt to bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 41. 40.</note> but ſuch was the goodneſſe of his nature, that in ſtead of falling vpon them to hurt them, <hi>he fell vpon them, kiſſed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 45. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>them, and wept vpon them:</hi> he kiſſed them becauſe hee loued them; he was glad to ſee them, and wept for ioy. Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lookes after matter to ſhew mercy, but baſeneſſe if it ſeemes an innocent, it is but for feare. <hi>Aut eius qui Patitur,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern. inſent.</note> 
                  <hi>ne reddat talionem,</hi> leſt the partie grieued right his owne wrongs, like the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> that had a will to try their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes againſt <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> as well as their neighbours, but the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15170:23"/>
example of <hi>Ierico</hi> &amp; <hi>Ai,</hi> made them afraid. If baſeneſſe ſeems <note place="margin">Ioſh. 9. 3.</note> an innocent, it is but for feare, 1. eyther leaſt the party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, right his owne wrongs: 2. or for feare, <hi>Superioris pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>ne inferat talionem;</hi> of the higher powers, leſt they pay wrong doing in it's owne kinde; like <hi>Agbarus,</hi> that would <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. Eccl. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> faine be doing with the Iewes, but for feare of the Romans. 3. or finally, for feare, <hi>Interioris Iudicijs, qui reddit vnicuique</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern. ibid.</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecundum opera ſua,</hi> of God, that rewardeth euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes; like <hi>Baalam,</hi> that was willing enough <note place="margin">Num. 22. 22. 24. 26.</note> to get <hi>Balak</hi> his money, and curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but for feare of the Angell that had like to haue killed him in the way. Now <hi>eam Deus Innocentiam probat, qua homo non poenae timore fit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocens,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de vera innocentia.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed amore iuſtitiae,</hi> God approues that man that is an Innocent, not for feare of puniſhment, but for loue of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>He is not an Innocent, blameleſſe and without fault, that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> offends not: but he is ſimply an innocent, blameleſſe and without fault, that offends not, not for feare of puniſhment, but for loue of vertue. <hi>Inimicus iuſtitiae eſt, qui poenae timore</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. epiſt.</hi> 144.</note> 
                  <hi>non peccat: amicus autem erit ſi eius amore non peccat,</hi> that man is auerſe to God and goodneſſe, that forbeares ill-doing, onely out of feare of puniſhment incident to ill-doing: but the man of God abſtaineth from ill-doing, out of the loue that he beareth to God and goodneſſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Oderunt peccare boni, virtutis amore. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Horat. Epiſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Num.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tu nihil admittes in te, formidine poenae.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quando timore poenae, non amore iuſtitiae fit bonum, nondum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. contra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. lib.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>fit bonum.</hi> When out of feare and not loue wee doe our duties, we doe that we ſhould, but not As we ſhould; we faile in the cauſe: <hi>Nec fit in corde, quod fieri videtur in opere, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do mallet homo non facere, ſi poſſet impune:</hi> there is a great deale of difference betweene the intention and the worke, when a man doth the good that he would not, becauſe hee durſt not otherwiſe doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:15170:24"/>
This ſhould teach vs to doe our duties, not out of feare, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> but loue, as God is a Father, not as he is a Iudge; becauſe we would not grieue him, not becauſe hee ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs. <hi>Nam qui gehennas metuit, non peccare metuit, ſed ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. epiſt.</hi> 144.</note> hee that is afraid of hell, is not afraid to ſinne, but to burne: <hi>ille autem peccare metuit, qui peccatum ipſum, ſicut ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hennas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>odit,</hi> but he is afraid to ſinne, that hateth ſinne, as he hateth hell. This is Louely, this is Douely innocence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> noteth in the Doue three things. 1. that ſhee neuer <note place="margin">Three remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Doue. <hi>Plin. hiſt. natur. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 34.</note> plaies falſe play with her mate. 2. that ſhe patiently without contradiction endures his imperious taunts of iealouſie. 3. that hee no ſooner offers reconciliation, but ſhee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines it, without retaining any thought of fore-paſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe: Whence we may obſerue likewiſe three proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in an Innocent: 1. that he offereth no wrong, 2. that <note place="margin">Three remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able properties in an Innocent</note> he patiently endureth wrong: 3. that he is eaſily reconciled after receiuing of wrong. Theſe generous ſciences graffed into the ſtocke of innocencie, take roote downeward, and beare fruit vpward: They take roote in the heart, the tongue, <note place="margin">Eſa. 37. 31.</note> and the hands; and beare fruit in thought, word, and deed. <hi>Who ſhal aſcend into the hil of the Lord, or who ſhall riſe vp in his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 24. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>holy place? Euen he that hath cleane hands and a pure heart, and that hath not lift vp his minde vnto vanitie, nor ſworne to deceiue his neighbour:</hi> An Innocent muſt haue 1. clean hands, 2. a pure heart, and 3. a warie tongue; He muſt haue clean hands, that neither force nor fraud marre his workes; hee muſt haue a pure heart, that neither ignorance nor wilfulneſſe corrupt his thoughts; hee muſt haue a warie tongue, that neither augmentation nor diminution diſproportion his words. The firſt is, <hi>Innocentia operis,</hi> the innocencie of the hands in <note place="margin">Bern. in ſent.</note> the worke; the ſecond is <hi>Innocentia ſermonis,</hi> the innocencie of the tongue in the word; the third is <hi>Innocentia cogitationis,</hi> the innocencie of the heart in the thought.</p>
               <p>To be abſolute in all Three, we muſt beware of a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Male,</hi> the firſt is, <hi>A Malefaciendo</hi> from ill-doing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in <hi>Malefacere opus eſt ſimulatorium, vel impium, vel im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudicum;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Berne. in ſent. Ibid.</note> the firſt is, <hi>cum aliud intendimus qùam opere demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtramus:</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15170:24"/>
When we intend one thing, and pretend another, like our wiſard <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> whileſt one lookes in your hand to tell you your Fortune, an others hand in your pocket is doing with your purſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Achilles apud. Hom. Illiad.</hi> 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</l>
               </q>
               <p>I cannot abide a man that carries two faces vnder one hood: A friend in ſhew, a foe in heart: This is <hi>Simulatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> Saint <hi>Martins</hi> Ware, counterfeit ſtuffe. The ſecond is <hi>Impium,</hi> ſinne and wickedneſſe; <hi>Cum proximum noſtrum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>ladimus:</hi> Like him that ſacrificeth (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> the <note place="margin">Aug.</note> ſonne in the ſight of the father, a ruthfull ſpectacle it were for a father to ſee his ſonne vpon the altar: a dolefull ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it is for the Sonne of God to feele his members maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred. He that ſacrificeth the ſonne muſt looke for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance from the Father: He that perſecuteth Ieſus Chriſt in his members, ſhall ſtand confounded, when the Lord <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1 7. 8.</note> Ieſus Chriſt ſhall ſhew himſelfe from Heauen, with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, rendring vengeance, vnto them that know not God, and which obey not vnto the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall be puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition, from the preſence of the Lord, <note place="margin">9.</note> and from the glory of his power; when hee ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to be made marueilous in all <note place="margin">10.</note> them that beleeue: This is, <hi>impium,</hi> ſinne. The next is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudicum,</hi> ſhame; <hi>Cum nos aliquo modo ſordidamus:</hi> When <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern. ſup. Plin. hiſt. natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis lib.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 10.</note> we defile our ſelues with our owne fleſh. Like the <hi>Panther</hi> that hath a longing after mans dung: Beaſts will doe their kinde, <hi>But fornication, and all vncleanneſſe, or couetouſneſſe, let</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>it not be once named among you.</hi> This is Innocencies firſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat, <hi>viz. a Malefaciendo.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>a Maledicendo,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern. in ſent.</note> from ill ſpeaking, becauſe in <hi>Maledicere, ſermo eſt vel ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacaneus, vel detractorius, vel adulatorius:</hi> The firſt is vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, the ſecond imputation, the third flattery. The firſt is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15170:25"/>
vaine <hi>Ratione &amp; vtilitate carens,</hi> to no purpoſe: Bragado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, <note place="margin">Bern. ſent.</note> Souldiers, and Trauellers; the one a vaine-glorious <hi>Thraſo,</hi> the other a Polytropian <hi>Vlyſſes.</hi> This is idle. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond derogatory, <hi>fraterna bona inuida corroſione, &amp; odij in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctu</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>diminuens:</hi> Leſſoning the good that is in another; like <hi>Zoylus,</hi> that barkes, becauſe he cannot bite. <hi>Quoniam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aelian. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ar. hiſt. lib.</hi> 11.</note> (ſaith he of himſelfe) <hi>malefacere quod vellem non poſſum, maledico,</hi> becauſe I cannot doe the euill that I haue a will to doe, I doe the euill that I can, I ſpeake ill: This is a peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie ſigne of a deboiſte nature: <hi>vilium ſatis hominum eſt, &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hieronimus.</note> 
                  <hi>ſuas landes quarentium alios viles facere: quia alterius vitupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſe laudari putant;</hi> this kills a man in the opinion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The third and laſt marres him in his own; <hi>Caputalicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>falſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lei delmitione demulcens,</hi> comming within a man to vndoe him: an Engliſh man Italianated, a deuill incarnated; like the Hyena that glauers with you till you truſt her, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. biſt. natur. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</note> then ſhe killes you. This is Innocencies ſecond bane, and we muſt beware of it.</p>
               <p>The third Caueat is <hi>a Male-Cogitando</hi> from ill-thinking, becauſe in <hi>Male-Cogitare eſt, vel immunditia, vel ſuperbia,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ſent.</note> 
                  <hi>vel auaritia:</hi> vncleaneneſſe, pride, or couetouſneſſe. The firſt is, <hi>cum res ſordidae &amp; impure memoria reuoluuntur;</hi> when <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> we defile our ſelues with the memorie of our owne pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This is their great and grieuous ſinne, that reckon vp their paſt eſcapes to glorie in them: This ſinne that good Father Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thus ſentenceth; <hi>Nullum ſcoelus tam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ad quendam Comit.</note> 
                  <hi>abhominabile eſt coram deo, quám praeterita peccata vnicuique noſtrum dimiſſa, reminiſcendo gaudere, &amp; inde exultare;</hi> God hates nothing ſo much, as to reckon vp old ſinnes, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in them; this is filthineſſe: The next is arrogancie; <hi>Cum animus quaſi ſuperior ſupra proximos ſuos erigitur &amp; inflatur;</hi> when a man thinkes that there is none ſo good as himſelfe, like <hi>Rabſache</hi> and <hi>Senacherib</hi> that inſulted ouer <hi>Hezekias</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Reg. cap. 18. &amp; 19. <hi>Iſiod. etim.</hi>
                  </note> the King of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the God thereof: <hi>Superbus dictus eſt, quia ſupra vult videri quàm eſt;</hi> A proud man will ſeeme to be more then he is; like <hi>Sabor</hi> in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> that pretended
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15170:25"/>
kindred to the Sunne; or <hi>Alexander</hi> in <hi>Curtius,</hi> that preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe to be the Sonne of <hi>Iupiter;</hi> or <hi>Simon Magus</hi> in <note place="margin">Acts 8. 9.</note> the Acts of the Apoſtles, that would needs bee ſome great man; or <hi>Lucifer,</hi> in the Prophet, that ſaid in his heart: <hi>I will</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 14. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>aſcend into heauen, and exalt my throne aboue, beſide the ſtarres of God: I will ſit alſo vpon the mount of the congregation, in the fides of the north. I will aſcend aboue the height of the clouds, and I will be like the moſt high:</hi> this is inſolencie. The next and laſt is Auarice: <hi>Cum diabolo inſtigante, contra praeceptum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>dei, res proximi concupiſcitur;</hi> When through the inſtigation of the diuell, we couet that that is none of our owne. Like the horſeleech, that ſtill crieth <hi>Giue, Giue,</hi> or hell and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <note place="margin">Prou. 30. 15.</note> that neuer haue enough; for, <hi>tam deeſt auaro</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 27. 29. <hi>Hier. ad Paulin.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quod habet, quàm quod non habet;</hi> the miſer wants as well what he hath, as what he hath not; and this is Innocencies third caueat; <hi>viz à Male-Cogitando: Say not then I will doe to him as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou 24. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>he hath done to me, recompence to no man euill for euill, be not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 17. Verſe 21.</note> 
                  <hi>of euill, but ouercome euill with good.</hi> The couetous man makes profit of his friend, the angry man workes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge on his enemy, the enuious man wiſheth well to no man, the cruell man will doe good to no man, but the Innocent man carrieth himſelfe towards his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hug. Card li.</hi> 2. <hi>de anima. cap.</hi> 9.</note> friend, <hi>ad gratiam,</hi> reſpectfully; towards his enemy, <hi>ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiam</hi> temperately; towards all men, <hi>ad beneuolentiam,</hi> to wiſh them well; towards as many as he can, <hi>ad beneficentiam,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in hom.</note> to doe them good: <hi>Gaude de innocentia &amp; exulta, gaude in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam quia vbique illaeſa eſt, vbique ſecura;</hi> Let thy innocence be thy ioy of heart: <hi>Si tentaris profitis,</hi> if thou be tempted, it is for thy good; <hi>for, bleſſed is the man that endureth tentation;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Si humiliaris erigeris,</hi> if thou be humbled, it is to exalt thee: <note place="margin">Luc. 14. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>for he that humbleth himſelfe, ſhall be exalted: Si pugnas vincis,</hi> if thou fighteſt, thou ſhalt ouercome, <hi>for a man cannot be an innocent and foyled: Si occideris coronaberis;</hi> if thou die for thy <note place="margin">1 Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 9.</note> conſcience, thou ſhalt be crowned for thy innocencie; for <note place="margin">Apoc. 7. 11.</note> he that dyes a Martyr, ſhall bee cloathed with the long white roabe of puritie. Labour, O labour to preſerue Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie in thought, word, and deed; for, as <hi>Pericles</hi> ſpake to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15170:26"/>
                  <hi>Sophocles,</hi> that a iudge muſt haue, <hi>non modo manus, ſed ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los etiam atque linguam abſtinentes,</hi> not onely cleane hands, but continent eyes alſo, and a warie tongue; ſo, he that will be abſolutely innocent, muſt looke not onely to his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but to his words alſo and thoughts to be iuſtified in all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſaid I will take heede vnto my wayes, that I offend not in my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 39. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>tongue;</hi> was the Kingly Prophet his reſolution. <hi>Pambo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. hiſt. eccl. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> thought this one line leſſon enough for ſixe moneths, and nineteene yeeres, little enough to learne perfectly this one point of innocency. <hi>Set a watch O Lord before my mouth, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 141. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>keepe the doore of my lippes:</hi> (ther's the innocency of the tongue;) <hi>O let not my heart be inclined to any euill thing;</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>4</label> (ther's the innocency of the heart) <hi>Let me not be occupied in vngodly workes</hi> (ther's the innocency of the hands.)</p>
               <p>Plants are firſt ſeedes, before they become to be vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues; Creatures are firſt Embrions, before they become to be ſenſitiues: and workes firſt thoughts, before they be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into actions. If therefore you would preuent the deede, you muſt not entertaine the thought: Now the will and the deede before God, are both alike; <hi>Voluntas pro opere</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ſup. Mat.</note> 
                  <hi>reputatur:</hi> God taketh the will for the deede. If a man hath a will to doe harme, <hi>Quamuis non nocot, cui vult nocere, &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de vera in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentia.</note> 
                  <hi>at ab iniquo opere, reus tamen fit ſola voluntate:</hi> Though hee doe no harme, yet his will to doe, makes him before God guilty of the harme.</p>
               <p>The Law (Right Reuerend) lyeth in your hands: <hi>quo plus poteſtis peccare, definite;</hi> Abuſe not your authority to doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice. <note place="margin">Seneca in Pro.</note> You are Sheepe, you might be Wolues: <hi>Poſſe &amp; nolle, nobile;</hi> It is a vertue not to doe all that a man may doe. Heauens ordinance hath made you Gods on Earth: Doue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 6.</note> innocency will make you Saints in Heauen.</p>
               <p>Innocency ſpeakes neither good of euill, nor euill of good. Beware (ye Gentry of the Countrey) how you aggrauate or extenuate any cauſe; becauſe, as <hi>Hecuba</hi> in <hi>Euripides</hi> ſpake to <hi>Vlyſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15170:26"/>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <note place="margin">Her: apud Eurip</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Your allegations are Axiomes, and according to your credit with the Iudge; ſo ſhall you doe either good or harme, by your report.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocens eſt, qui cum alijs non nocet, nec ſibi nocet.</hi> An inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug: in Pſa.</hi> 38</note> wrongs neither others nor his owne conſcience, in eyther iuſtifying the wicked, or condemning the innocent. Yee good men of the <hi>Iurie,</hi> are held for ſheepe, O bee not Wolues in Sheepes cloathing: You are thought to be wiſe as ſerpents, to preſerue the head, O ſpend not your venome vpon the members: You ſhould bee Doues for your inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, O bee not Apodes for your partialitie, alwayes in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. hiſt. in l.</hi> 10. <hi>ca.</hi> 39.</note> extremities, eyther flying with the plaintiffe, or lying downe with the defendant: you are iudges <hi>de facto,</hi> you muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, you muſt haue no reſpect of perſons <note place="margin">Deut. 1. 17.</note> in iudgement, you muſt follow your Euidence, and finde <hi>ſecundum allegata &amp; probata,</hi> as you haue proofe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you.</p>
               <p>Finally what man is hee that luſteth to liue, and would <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> faine ſee good dayes? <hi>Keepe thy tongue from euill, and thy lippes that they ſpeake no guile. Eſchew euill and doe good, ſeeke</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>13</label> 
                  <hi>peace and enſue it.</hi> Or would you haue good dayes while you liue, and peace at the end? Keepe innocencie and doe <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 38.</note> the thing that is right: for that ſhall bring a man peace at the laſt.</p>
               <p>Hee that would dye Peaceably muſt liue innocently: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> in thought, word and deed; not onely Doing but ſuffering alſo innocently.</p>
               <p>It is obſerued in the Doue, that ſhe not onely neuer plaies <note place="margin">Ser. 2. fol. 42.</note> falſe play with her mate; but that therewithall ſhee patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo vndergoes his imperiall taunts of Ielouſie; to teach vs that</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15170:27"/>
Douely innocencie is not onely the forbearing of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> wrong doing, but the patient-bearing alſo of wrong offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; the firſt is, <hi>Omnem iniuriae illationem abhorrens:</hi> an vtter <note place="margin">Cic: offic.</note> deteſtation of all wrong doing. To this are men tied by the law of nature: <hi>Homo naturae obediens, homini nocere non poteſt.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Idem Ibid.</note> If we conforme our ſelues in obedience vnto nature, wee cannot offer any violence, one man to an other. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug: quaeſt.</hi> 83. <hi>quaeſ.</hi> 31.</note> is, <hi>Honeſtatis cauſa rerum difficilium voluntaria ac diuturna perpeſſio:</hi> A noble entertainement of a good cauſe, though we ſuffer for it, eyther in Chriſt, as all good Chriſtians, for hereunto are yee called, for Chriſt alſo ſuffered for vs, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 21.</note> vs an example that we ſhould follow his ſteppes; or for Chriſt as Martyres and confeſſors, bleſſed in ſuffering for <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 10.</note> Righteouſneſſe ſake, <hi>aequo non iniquo animo,</hi> willingly and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug: de pat. cap:</hi> 2.</note> innocentlie: for this is thankes worthie, if a man for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience toward God endure griefe, ſuffering wrongfully: <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 19.</note> and that becauſe,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Hee will not take Gods office out of his hands, to <note place="margin">Reaſons.</note> worke his owne reuenge, for, <hi>vengeance is mine, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay, ſayth the Lord.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, He waiteth patiently Gods leaſure, in hope at laſt to be deliuered. <hi>Say not thou I will recompenſe euill: but</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>waite vpon the Lord, and he ſhall ſaue thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Though hee bee not for the preſent deliuered: yet he is reſolued, <hi>that the afflictions of this preſent time, are not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>worthy of the glory that ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, In the interim he poſſeſſeth his ſoule by patience <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 19. is maſter of himſelfe, and calmeth natures out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages. <hi>He that is ſlow vnto anger, is better then the mighty man:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>and hee that ruleth his owne minde, is better then hee that win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a Citie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, Hee knowes not what good his example may doe, <hi>Ye haue heard of the patience of Iob: and haue knowne what end</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Io. 5. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord made,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When man, by perſecution, goes about to trouble thee: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> or the deuill by temptation to ſeduce thee: or God by his croſſe to proue thee, take heede: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg: homil.</hi> 35.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15170:27"/>
Firſt, <hi>Ne contra mala proximi pertrahatur mens ad retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem mali,</hi> leaſt thou thinke vpon reuenge, to doe as thou art done vnto. <hi>Loue your enemies, bleſſe them that curſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>doe good to them that hate you, and pray for them which hurt you, and perſecute you,</hi> This is God his proceeding with <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>45</label> man, this ſhould mans proceeding bee with his brethren: <note place="margin">Ver. 46, 47, 41.</note> Take heede,</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Ne contra tentamenta aduerſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeducatur ad</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Greg: ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>delectationem vel conſenſum delicti.</hi> Leaſt thou yeeld to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptation. <hi>Tentare poteſt, vincere non poteſt niſi conſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aris;</hi> Though Satan worketh vpon the will, yet it muſt bee our conſent that acts the ſinne; <hi>Suggerere poteſt, cogere non</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. in mat.</note> 
                  <hi>poteſt;</hi> he can but moue, he cannot force.</p>
               <p>The third care is, <hi>Ne contra flagella opificis proruat ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Greg: ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>murmurationis;</hi> leaſt we repine at his viſitation: <hi>For the Lord correcteth him whom he loueth, euen as a Father doth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 3. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the childe in whom he delighteth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And heere are we affronted with a three fold vexation in our ſuffering, the firſt is, <hi>Cauſa iuſta innocentis,</hi> the innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie <note place="margin">Bern: inſenten.</note> of the partie ſuffering: <hi>But it is better if the will of God be ſo that ye ſuffer for well doing, then for euill doing.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 17.</note> is, <hi>Anxietas nimia doloris,</hi> extremitie of ſorrow becauſe of our ſuffering; But God is faithfull, who will not ſuffer <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 13.</note> you to be tempted aboue that you be able, but will giue you the iſſue with the tentation, that ye may be able to beare it. The third is, the vnworthineſſe of the inflicter, when the creature that ſhould bee our ſeruant becomes our tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodor: ſer.</hi> 3. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t non Deo: it a creaturae nobis inſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt. Cypr. tract.</hi> 1. <hi>Cont. Demetr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non immerito reluctantur beſtiae hominibus, quam ipſi Deo ſuo rebelles ſint.</hi> How ſhould the creature ſerue vs, if we ſerue not God? Or when men that ſhould bee as the ſhepheard and the ſheepe; as a turtle &amp; her mate, become notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Wolues inſtead of Shepheards, and Harpies inſtead of Doues, O but did <hi>the wayes of a man pleaſe the Lord, he would</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou 16. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>then make all his enemies at peace with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tu ne cede malis: ſed contra audentior ito.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg: aeneid. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Eccleſi</hi> 28. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Magna eſt virtus, ſi non laedas a quo laeſus es. Magna eſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15170:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15170:28"/>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15170:29"/>
                  <hi>ſi etiam laeſus remittas. Magna eſt gloria ſi cui potuiſti no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, parcas:</hi> It is great worth in a man to forbeare to repay <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſidor: ſoliloq:</hi> 2.</note> ill, magnanimitie and glory to forgiue and forget. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in the Doue, firſt, that ſhe neuer playes falſe play <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. fol</hi> 42.</note> with her mate; ſecondly, that ſhe patiently beares with his cauſeleſſe iealouſie; thirdly, that he no ſooner offers recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation but ſhe retaines it: To teach vs that,</p>
               <p>An innocent &amp; good man is eaſily pacified, ſoone reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Toleraſſe &amp; odiſſe non eſt virtus manſuetudinis, ſed velamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg: homil.</hi> 7. <hi>ſup. Ezek.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>furoris:</hi> He doth not only forgiue, but forget alſo; the reaſon is, becauſe God will not forgiue vs, except we forgiue our brethren. Should a man beare hatred againſt man, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <note place="margin">Eccle. 28. 3.</note> forgiueneſſe of the Lord? <hi>If you forgiue men their treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, your heauenly Father will alſo forgiue you: But if you doe not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>forgiue men their treſpaſſes, no more will your father forgiue you your treſpaſſes.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The recompenſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes is forgiuenes; mens forgiuing of men, to bee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> forgiuen of God.</p>
               <p>Forgiue therefore, and it ſhall be forgiuen: Be curteous <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> one to another &amp; tender-hearted, forgiuing one another, as God, for Chriſts ſake forgaue you. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 32.</note> Hath God for Chriſts ſake forgiuen you? for his ſake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue <note place="margin">Nazian.</note> you one another: Hath God for Chriſts ſake forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <note place="margin">Matt. 28. 24.</note> thee tenue thouſand talents? wilt not thou for his ſake <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>28</label> forgiue thy brother an hundred pence? <hi>Quantum vis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti tibi, tantum dimitte, quoties vis dimitti tibi, toties tu dimitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Petr. Chryſoſt. ſer.</hi> 67.</note> Looke how much and how oft thou wouldeſt be forgiuen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo much and ſo oft doe thou forgiue. And God, who is rich in mercie, make you perfect in euery good worke, working in you that which is pleaſant in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
